Bookwix IV.
The ghosts of the suitors and haids, Ulysses and his men go to the house of Lurtas.
The people of Ithaca come out to attack Ulysses, but Minerva concludes apiece.
Then Mercury of Cilene summoned the ghosts of the suitors, and in his hand he held the fair golden wand, with which he seals men's eyes in sleep, or wakes them just as he pleases.
With this he roused the ghosts and led them, while they followed whining and gibbering behind him.
As bats fly squealing in the hollow of some great cave, when one of them has fallen out of the cluster in which they hang, even so did the ghosts whine and squeal as Mercury, the healer of sorrow, led them down into the dark abode of death.
When they had passed the waters of Oceanus and the rock Leucus,
They came to the gates of the sun and the land of dreams, whereon they reached the meadow of Asphodel, where dwell the souls and shadows of them that can labour no more.
Here they found the ghost of Achilles son of Peleus, with those of Patroclus, Antilochus, and Ajax, who was the finest and handsomest man of all the Danaeans after the son of Peleus himself.
They gathered round the ghost of the son of Peleus, and the ghost of Agamemnon joined them, sorrowing bitterly.
Round him were gathered also the ghosts of those who had perished with him in the house of Aegisthus, and the ghost of Achilles spoke first.
Son of Atreus, it said, we used to say that Jove had loved you better from first to last than any other hero, for you were captain over many and brave men when we were all fighting together before Troy.
yet the hand of death, which no mortal can escape, was laid upon you all too early.
Better for you had you fallen at Troy in the heyday of your renown, for the Achaeans would have built a mound over your ashes,
your son would have been heir to your good name, whereas it has now been your lot to come to a most miserable end.
Happy son of Peleus," answered the ghost of Agamemnon, for having died at Troy far from Argos, while the bravest of the Trojans and the Achaeans fell round you fighting for your body, there you lay in the whirling clouds of dust, all huge and hugely heedless now of your chivalry.
We fought the whole of the livelong day, nor should we ever have left off if Jove had not sent a hurricane to stay us.
Then, when we had borne you to the ships out of the fray, we laid you on your bed and cleansed your fair skin with warm water and with ointments.
The Deneans tore their hair and wept bitterly round about you.
Your mother, when she heard, came with her immortal nymphs from out of the sea,
and the sound of a great wailing went forth over the waters, so that the Achaeans quaked for fear.
They would have fled panic-stricken to their ships, had not wise old Nestor, whose counsel was ever truest, checked them, saying, Hold, Argives!
Fly not, sons of the Achaeans!
This is his mother coming from the sea with her immortal nymphs to view the body of her son.
Thus he spoke, and the Achaeans feared no more.
The daughters of the old man of the sea stood round you weeping bitterly and clothed you in immortal raiment.
The nigh muses also came and lifted up their sweet voices in lament, calling and answering one another.
There was not an argive but wept for pity of the dirge they chanted.
Days and nights, seven and ten, we mourned you, mortals and immortals.
But on the eighteenth day we gave you to the flames, and many a fat sheep with many an ox did we slay and sacrifice around you.
You were burnt in raiment of the gods, with rich resins and with honey, while heroes, horse and foot, clashed their armour round the pile as you were burning, with the tramp as of a great multitude.
But when the flames of heaven had done their work, we gathered your white bones at daybreak and laid them in ointments and in pure wine.
Your mother brought us a golden vase to hold them, gift of Bacchus, and work of Vulcan himself.
In this we mingled your bleached bones with those of Patroclus who had gone before you, and separate we enclosed also those of Antilochus, who had been closer to you than any other of your comrades now that Patroclus was no more.
Over these the host of the Argives built a noble tomb,
on a point jutting out over the open hellespont that it might be seen from far out upon the sea by those now living and by them that shall be born hereafter.
Your mother begged prizes from the gods and offered them to be contended for by the noblest of the Achaeans.
You must have been present at the funeral of many a hero when the young men gird themselves and make ready to contend for prizes on the death of some great chieftain,
But you never saw such prizes as silver-footed Thetis offered in your honor, for the gods loved you well.
Thus even in death your fame, Achilles, has not been lost, and your name lives evermore among all mankind.
But as for me, what solace had I when the days of my fighting were done?
For Jove willed my destruction on my return by the hands of Aegisthus and those of my wicked wife.
Thus did they converse, and presently Mercury came up to them with the ghosts of the suitors who had been killed by Ulysses,
The ghosts of Agamemnon and Achilles were astonished at seeing them, and went up to them at once.
The ghost of Agamemnon recognized Amphimedon son of Melanius, who lived in Ithaca and had been his host, so it began to talk to him.
What has happened to all you fine young men, all of an age too, that you are come down here under the ground?
One could pick no finer body of men from any city.
Did Neptune raise his winds and waves against you when you were at sea?
Or did your enemies make an end of you on the mainland when you were cattle lifting or sheep stealing or while fighting in defense of their wives and city?
Answer my question, for I have been your guest.
Do you not remember how I came to your house with Menelaus to persuade Ulysses to join us with his ships against Troy?
It was a whole month ere we could resume our voyage, for we had hard work to persuade Ulysses to come with us.
And the ghost of Amphimodon answered, Agamemnon, son of Atreus, king of men, I remember everything that you have said and will tell you fully and accurately about the way in which our end was brought about.
Ulysses had been long gone, and we were courting his wife, who did not say point-blank that she would not marry nor yet bring matters to an end, for she meant to compass our destruction.
This, then, was the trick she played us.
She set up a great tambour frame in her room and began to work on an enormous piece of fine needlework.
"'Sweethearts,' said she, "'Ulysses is indeed dead.
Still, do not press me to marry again immediately.
Wait, for I would not have my skill in needlework perish unrecorded till I have completed a pall for the hero Laertes against the time when death shall take him.
He is very rich, and the women of the place will talk if he is laid out without a pall.'
This is what she said, and we assented, whereupon we could see her working upon her great web all day long, but at night she would unpick the stitches again by torchlight.
She fooled us in this way for three years without our finding it out, but as time wore on, and she was now in her fourth year, in the waning of moons and many days had been accomplished, one of her maids who knew what she was doing told us, and we caught her in the act of undoing her work,
So she had to finish it whether she would or no, and when she showed us the robe she had made, after she had had it washed when eighty-six, its splendour was as that of the sun or moon.
Then some malicious god conveyed Ulysses to the upland farm where his swineherd lives.
Thither presently came also his son, returning from a voyage to Pylos, and the two came to the town when they had hatched their plot for our destruction.
Telemachus came first, and then after him, accompanied by the swineherd, came Ulysses, clad in rags and leaning on a staff as though he were some miserable old beggar.
He came so unexpectedly that none of us knew him, not even the older ones among us, and we reviled him and threw things at him.
He endured both being struck and insulted without a word, though he was in his own house, but when the will of Aegis bearing Jove inspired him, he and Telemachus took the armor and hid it in an inner chamber, bolting the doors behind them.
Then he cunningly made his wife offer his bow and a quantity of iron to be contended for by us ill-fated suitors, and this was the beginning of our end, for not one of us could string the bow, nor nearly do so.
When it was about to reach the hands of Ulysses, we all of us shouted out that it should not be given him, no matter what he might say, but Telemachus insisted on his having it.
When he had got it in his hands, he strung it with ease and sent his arrow through the iron.
Then he stood on the floor of the cloister and poured his arrows on the ground, glaring fiercely about him.
First he killed Antinous, and then, aiming straight before him, he let fly his deadly darts, and they fell thick on one another.
It was plain that someone of the gods was helping them, for they fell upon us with might and maim throughout the cloisters, and there was a hideous sound of groaning as our brains were being battered in and the ground seethed with our blood.
This, Agamemnon, is how we came by our end, and our bodies are lying still uncared for in the house of Ulysses, for our friends at home do not yet know what has happened, so that they cannot lay us out and wash the black blood from our wounds, making moan over us according to the officers due to the departed.
Happy Ulysses, son of Laertes, replied the ghost of Agamemnon, you are indeed blessed in the possession of a wife endowed with such rare excellence of understanding, and so faithful to her wedded lord as Penelope the daughter of Icarius.
The fame therefore of her virtue shall never die, and the immortals shall compose a song that shall be welcomed to all mankind in honor of the constancy of Penelope.
How far otherwise was the wickedness of the daughter of Tyndareus who killed her lawful husband, her song shall be hateful among men, for she has brought disgrace on all womankind even on the good ones.
Thus did they converse in the house of Hades deep down within the bowels of the earth.
Meanwhile Ulysses and the others passed out of the town, and soon reached the fair and well-tealed farm of Laertes, which he had reclaimed with infinite labor.
Here was his house, with a lean-to running all round it, where the slaves who worked for him slept and sat and ate, while inside the house there was an old Sicil woman who looked after him in this his country farm.
When Ulysses got there, he said to his son and to the other two, go to the house and kill the best pig that you can find for dinner.
Meanwhile, I want to see whether my father will know me or fail to recognize me after so long an absence.
He then took off his armor and gave it to Eumaeus and Philoetius, who went straight on to the house while he turned off into the vineyard to make trial of his father.
As he went down into the great orchard, he did not see Dolius, nor any of his sons, nor of the other bondsmen, for they were all gathering thorns to make a fence for the vineyard, at the place where the old man had told them, he therefore found his father alone, hoeing a vine.
He had on a dirty old shirt, patched and very shabby.
His legs were bound round with thongs of oxide to save him from the brambles, and he also wore sleeves of leather.
He had a goatskin cap on his head and was looking very woe-begone.
When Ulysses saw him so worn, so old and full of sorrow, he stood still under a tall pear tree and began to weep.
He doubted whether to embrace him, kiss him, and tell him all about his having come home, or whether he should first question him and see what he would say.
In the end, he deemed it best to be crafty with him, so in this mind he went up to his father, who was bending down and digging about a plant.
"'I see, sir,' said Ulysses, "'that you are an excellent gardener, what pains you take with it, to be sure.
There is not a single plant, not a fig tree, vine, olive, pear, nor flower-bed, but bears the trace of your attention.
I trust, however, that you will not be offended if I say that you take better care of your garden than of yourself.
You are old, unsavoury, and very meanly clad.
It cannot be because you are idle that your master takes such poor care of you.
Indeed, your face and figure have nothing of the slave about them, and proclaim you of noble birth.
I should have said that you were one of those who should wash well, eat well, and lie soft at night as old men have a right to do.
But tell me, and tell me true, whose bondman are you, and in whose garden are you working?
Tell me also about another matter.
Is this place that I have come to really Ithaca?
I met a man just now who said so, but he was a dull fellow and had not the patience to hear my story out when I was asking him about an old friend of mine, whether he was still living or was already dead and in the house of Hades.
Believe me when I tell you that this man came to my house once when I was in my own country, and never yet did any stranger come to me whom I liked better.
He said that his family came from Ithaca, and that his father was Laertes, son of Arcesius.
I received him hospitably, making him welcome to all the abundance of my house, and when he went away I gave him all customary presents.
I gave him seven talents of fine gold, and a cup of solid silver with flowers chased upon it.
I gave him twelve light cloaks, and as many pieces of tapestry, I also gave him twelve cloaks of single fold, twelve rugs, twelve fair mantles, and an equal number of shirts.
To all this I added four good-looking women skilled in all useful arts, and I let him take his choice.
His father shed tears and answered, Sir, you have indeed come to the country that you have named, but it has fallen into the hands of wicked people.
All this wealth of presents has been given to no purpose.
If you could have found your friend here alive in Ithaca, he would have entertained you hospitably and would have requited your presents amply when you left him, as would have been only right considering what you had already given him.
But tell me, and tell me true, how many years is it since you entertained this guest, my unhappy son, as ever was?
Alas, he has perished far from his own country, the fishes of the sea have eaten him, or he has fallen a prey to the birds and wild beasts of some continent.
Neither his mother, nor I his father, who were his parents, could throw our arms about him and wrap him in his shroud, nor could his excellent and richly dowered wife Penelope bewail her husband as was natural upon his deathbed, and close his eyes according to the offices due to the departed.
But now tell me truly, for I want to know.
Who and whence are you tell me of your town and parents?
Where is the ship lying that has brought you and your men to Ithaca?
Or were you a passenger on some other man's ship, and those who brought you here have gone on their way and left you?"
"'I will tell you everything,' answered Ulysses, quite truly.
"'I come from Alibas, where I have a fine house.
I am son of King Aphidas, who is the son of Polypemon.
My own name is Iperitus.
Heaven drove me off my course as I was leaving Cycania, and I have been carried here against my will.
As for my ship, it is lying over yonder, off the open country outside the town, and this is the fifth year since Ulysses left my country.
Poor fellow, yet the omens were good for him when he left me.
The birds all flew on our right hands, and both he and I rejoiced to see them as we parted,
for we had every hope that we should have another friendly meeting and exchange presents.
A dark cloud of sorrow fell upon Laertes as he listened.
He filled both hands with the dust from off the ground and poured it over his gray head, groaning heavily as he did so.
The heart of Ulysses was touched, and his nostrils quivered as he looked upon his father.
Then he sprang towards him, flung his arms about him and kissed him, saying, I am he, father, about whom you are asking.
I have returned after having been away for twenty years.
But cease your sighing and lamentation.
We have no time to lose, for I should tell you that I have been killing the suitors in my house, to punish them for their insolence and crimes.
If you really are my son Ulysses, replied Laertes, and have come back again, you must give me such manifest proof of your identity as shall convince me.
"'First observe this scar,' answered Ulysses, which I got from a boar's tusk when I was hunting on Mantine on Mantida Beauty.
Parnassus, you and my mother had sent me to Autolychus, my mother's father, to receive the presents which, when he was over here, he had promised to give me.
Furthermore, I will point out to you the trees in the vineyard which you gave me, and I asked you all about them as I followed you round the garden.
We went over them all, and you told me their names and what they all were.
You gave me thirteen pear trees, ten apple trees, and forty fig trees.
You also said you would give me fifty rows of vines.
There was corn planted between each row, and they yield grapes of every kind when the heat of heaven has been laid heavy upon them.
Laertes' strength failed him when he heard the convincing proofs which his son had given him.
He threw his arms about him, and Ulysses had to support him, or he would have gone off into a swoon.
But as soon as he came to, and was beginning to recover his senses, he said, O father Jove, then you gods are still in Olympus after all, if the suitors have really been punished for their insolence and folly.
Nevertheless, I am much afraid that I shall have all the townspeople of Ithaca up here directly, and they will be sending messengers everywhere throughout the cities of the Cephalenians."
Ulysses answered, "'Take heart, and do not trouble yourself about that, but let us go into the house hard by your garden.'"
I have already told Telemachus, Phileucius, and Eumaeus to go on there and get dinner ready as soon as possible."
Thus conversing the two made their way towards the house.
When they got there they found Telemachus with the stockman and the swineherd cutting up meat and mixing wine with water.
Then the old cycle woman took Laertes inside and washed him and anointed him with oil.
She put him on a good cloak, and Minerva came up to him and gave him a more imposing presence, making him taller and stouter than before.
When he came back his son was surprised to see him looking so like an immortal, and said to him, My dear father, some one of the gods has been making you much taller and better looking.
Laertes answered, Would by Father Jove, Minerva, and Apollo, that I were the man I was when I ruled among the Cephalenians, and took Nerechem, that strong fortress on the foreland.
If I were still what I then was and had been in our house yesterday with my armor on, I should have been able to stand by you and help you against the suitors.
I should have killed a great many of them, and you would have rejoiced to see it."
Thus did they converse.
But the others, when they had finished their work and the feast was ready, left off working and took each his proper place on the benches and seats.
Then they began eating.
By and by old Dolius and his sons left their work and came up, for their mother,
The Sicil woman, who looked after Laertes now that he was growing old, had been to fetch them.
When they saw Ulysses and were certain it was he, they stood there lost in astonishment.
But Ulysses scolded them good-naturedly and said, Sit down to your dinner, old man, and never mind about your surprise.
We have been wanting to begin for some time and have been waiting for you.
Then Dolius put out both his hands and went up to Ulysses.
Sir, said he, seizing his master's hand and kissing it at the wrist, we have long been wishing you home.
and now heaven has restored you to us after we had given up hoping.
All hail, therefore, and may the gods prosper you.187 But tell me, does Penelope already know of your return, or shall we send someone to tell her?
Old man, answered Ulysses, she knows already, so you need not trouble about that.
On this he took his seat, and the sons of Dolius gathered round Ulysses to give him greeting and embrace him one after the other.
Then they took their seats in due order near Dolius their father.
While they were thus busy getting their dinner ready, rumour went round the town, and noised abroad the terrible fate that had befallen the suitors.
As soon, therefore, as the people heard of it they gathered from every quarter, groaning and hooting before the house of Ulysses.
They took the dead away, buried every man his own, and put the bodies of those who came from elsewhere on board the fishing vessels, for the fisherman to take each of them to his own place.
They then met angrily in the place of assembly, and when they were got together Eupathes rose to speak.
He was overwhelmed with grief for the death of his son Antinous, who had been the first man killed by Ulysses, so he said, weeping bitterly.
My friends, this man has done the Achaeans great wrong.
He took many of our best men away with him in his fleet, and he has lost both ships and men.
Now, moreover, on his return he has been killing all the foremost men among the Cephalenians.
Let us be up and doing before he can get away to Pylos, or to Elis where the Aepians rule, or we shall be ashamed of ourselves forever afterwards.
It will be an everlasting disgrace to us if we do not avenge the murder of our sons and brothers.
For my own part, I should have no more pleasure in life, but had rather die at once.
Let us be up then and after them before they can cross over to the mainland."
He wept as he spoke, and everyone pitied him.
But Medon and the bard Phemius had now woke up and came to them from the house of Ulysses.
Everyone was astonished at seeing them, but they stood in the middle of the assembly and Medon said, Hear me, men of Ithaca.
Ulysses did not do these things against the will of heaven.
I myself saw an immortal god take the form of mentor and stand beside him.
This god appeared, now in front of him encouraging him, and now going furiously about the court.
and attacking the suitors whereon they fell thick on one another.
On this pale fear laid hold of them, and old Halitherse's son of master rose to speak, for he was the only man among them who knew both past and future.
So he spoke to them plainly and in all honesty, saying, Men of Ithaca, it is all your own fault that things have turned out as they have.
You would not listen to me, nor yet to mentor, when we bade you check the folly of your sons who were doing much wrong in the wantonness of their hearts, wasting the substance and dishonoring the wife of a chieftain who they thought would not return.
Now, however, let it be as I say, and do as I tell you.
Do not go out against Ulysses, or you may find that you have been drawing down evil on your own heads.
This was what he said, and more than half raised a loud shout and at once left the assembly.
But the rest stayed where they were, for the speech of Halithursus displeased them, and they sided with Eupathes.
They therefore hurried off for their armour, and when they had armed themselves they met together in front of the city, and Eupathes led them on in their folly.
He thought he was going to avenge the murder of his son, whereas in truth he was never to return, but was himself to perish in his attempt.
Then Minerva said to Jove, Father, son of Saturn, king of kings, answer me this question, what do you propose to do?
Will you set them fighting still further, or will you make peace between them?
And Jove answered, My child, why should you ask me?
Was it not by your own arrangement that Ulysses came home and took his revenge upon the suitors?
Do whatever you like, but I will tell you what I think will be most reasonable arrangement.
Now that Ulysses is revenged, let them swear to a solemn covenant, in virtue of which he shall continue to rule, while we cause the others to forgive and forget the massacre of their sons and brothers.
Let them then all become friends as heretofore, and let peace and plenty reign."
This was what Minerva was already eager to bring about, so down she darted from off the topmost summits of Olympus.
Now, when Laertes and the others had done dinner, Ulysses began by saying, Some of you go out and see if they are not getting close up to us.
So one of Dolius's sons went as he was bid.
Standing on the threshold, he could see them all quite near, and said to Ulysses, Here they are.
Let us put on our armor at once.
They put on their armor as fast as they could, that is to say, Ulysses, his three men, and the six sons of Dolius.
Laertes also and Dolius did the same, warriors by necessity, in spite of their gray hair.
When they had all put on their armor, they opened the gate and sallied forth, Ulysses leading the way.
Then Jove's daughter Minerva came up to them, having assumed the form and voice of mentor.
Ulysses was glad when he saw her, and said to his son Telemachus, Telemachus, now that you are about to fight in an engagement, which will show every man's mettle, be sure not to disgrace your ancestors who were eminent for their strength and courage all the world over.
You say truly, my dear father, answered Telemachus, and you shall see, if you will, that I am in no mind to disgrace your family.
Laertes was delighted when he heard this.
Good heavens!
he exclaimed.
What a day I am enjoying!
I do indeed rejoice at it.
My son and grandson are vying with one another in the matter of valour.
On this Minerva came close up to him and said, Son of Arsetius, best friend I have in the world, pray to the blue-eyed damsel, and to Jove her father, then poise your spear and hurl it.
As she spoke she infused fresh vigour into him, and when he had prayed to her he poised his spear and hurled it.
He hit Eupethes' helmet, and the spear went right through it, for the helmet stayed at naught, and his armor rang rattling round him as he fell heavily to the ground.
Meantime, Ulysses and his son fell upon the front line of the foe, and smote them with their swords and spears.
Indeed, they would have killed every one of them, and prevented them from ever getting home again.
Only Minerva raised her voice aloud, and made everyone pause.
Men of Ithaca, she cried, cease this dreadful war, and settle the matter at once without further bloodshed.
On this pale fear seized everyone.
They were so frightened that their arms dropped from their hands and fell upon the ground at the sound of the goddess' voice, and they fled back to the city for their lives.
But Ulysses gave a great cry, and gathering himself together swooped down like a soaring eagle.
Then the son of Saturn sent a thunderbolt of fire that fell just in front of Minerva, so she said to Ulysses, Ulysses, noble son of Laertes, stop this warful strife, or Jove will be angry with you.
Thus spoke Minerva, and Ulysses obeyed her gladly.
Then Minerva assumed the form and voice of Mentor and presently made a covenant of peace between the two contending parties.
Footnotes, one-toon black races are evidently known to the writer as stretching all across Africa, one half looking west onto the Atlantic and the other east onto the Indian Ocean.
The original use of the footstool was probably less to rest the feet than to keep them, especially when bare from a floor which was often wet and dirty.
3.
The thirtenmieter, or seat, is occasionally called high as being higher than the thirtenmieter, or low footstool.
It was probably no higher than an ordinary chair is now, and seems to have had no back.
Thirtenfortenmieter and mieter was on the west coast of the Toa of Italy, in what is now the Gulf of Stalyephemia.
It was famous in remote times for its copper mines, which, however, were worked out when Straubel wrote, Five photo I E with a current in it.
See illustrations and map near the end of BKS.
V and VI, respectively.
One B, respectively, GE.
My four I AI.
Corner C, meter, four I, GE.
Eight I I. Eight I I. Eight I one, where the same mistake is made, and ZEE.
351, where the mountain is called Neritum, the same place being intended both here and in Book Xiyi.
Xiyi.
It is never plausibly explained why Penelope cannot do this, and from BK.
Ai Ai.
It is clear that she kept on deliberately encouraging the suitors, though we are asked to believe that she was only fooling them.
28, 282.
See note on odd.
I, Thucyc 5, 282.
9 to middle Argos means the Peloponnese, which, however, is never so called in the Iliad.
I presume middle means middle between the two Greek-speaking countries of Asia Minor and Sicily, with South Italy.
For that, parts of Sicily, and also large parts, though not the whole of South Italy, were inhabited by Greek-speaking races centuries before the Dorian colonizations can hardly be doubted.
The Scythians, and also the Scythians, both of them probably spoke Greek.
10.
NTCF.
Il.
Vi.
490T.
2TCF.
Il.
Vi.
490T.
22TT.
HCF.
In the Iliad, it is war, not speech.
That is a man's matter.
It argues a certain hardness, or at any rate dislike, of the Iliad on the part of the writer of the Odyssey that she should have adopted Hector's farewell to Andromache here, as elsewhere in the poem, for a scene of such inferior pathos.
Tignel.
Tignor.
The whole open court with the covered cloister running round it was called Tignor, Tignor, or Ainor.
But the covered part was distinguished by being called Shady or Shadowgiving.
It was in this part that the tables for the suitors were laid.
The fountain court at Hampton Court may serve as an illustration, save as regards the use of arches instead of wooden supports and rafters, and the arrangement is still common in Sicily.
The usual translation, shadowy or dusky halls, gives a false idea of the scene.
12.
The reader will note the extreme care which the writer takes to make it clear that none of the suitors were allowed to sleep in Ulysses' house.
2023.
See Appendix.
G. In plan of Ulysses' house.
2020-20.
I imagine this passage to be a rejoinder to Ill.
XXXI.
702-705, in which a tripod is valued at twelve oxen, and a good useful maid of all work at only four.
The scrupulous regard of Laertes for his wife's feelings is of a piece with the extreme jealousy for the honour of woman, which is manifest throughout the Odyssey.
Minister 15-5 de Thurce.
Minister V to the NCs, the first to V to laities, or Tunisica, was a shirt or shift, and served as the chief undergarment of the Greeks and Romans, whether men or women.
Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities under Tunisica.
16.
Doors fastened to all intents and purposes, as here described, may be seen in the older houses at Trapani.
There is a slot on the outer side of the door by means of which a person who has left the room can shoot the bolt.
My bedroom at the albergo centrale was fastened in this way.
To 17197.
The Bliaur.
so we vulgarly say had cooked his goose, or had settled his hash.
Egyptians cannot of course know of the fate Antiphas had met with, for there had as yet been no news of or from Ulysses.new18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18.ilz.u18
The authoress has bungled by borrowing these words verbatim from the Iliad, which I have supplied, Nineteen in mine tea, in mine tea, in mine tea.
I een mine teen, mine tea, dotchy, dotch, nineteen in mine.
You have money, and could pay when I got judgment, whereas the suitors are men of straw, to twenty CF.
Ill, I-I, seventy-six.
Y-I-I-pline is I-I-I-I-I-I.
Y-I-I-I-I-I-I-I.
Y-I-I-I-I-I-I.
Y-I-I-ni-I-I-I-di-I-I-I-di-I-I-I-I-di-I-I-I-di-I-si-I-di-I.
The Odaiai Palmessage runs, Is it possible not to suspect that the name Mentor was coined upon that of Nestor?
21 21, e.i.e.
in the outer court and in the uncovered part of the inner house.
22 1
This would be fair from Sicily, which was doing duty for Ithaca in the mind of the writer, but a north wind would have been preferable for a voyage from the real Ithaca to Pylos.
23.
Does nigh too whizz cition.
Does not whizzle over waves.
The wind does not whistle over waves.
It only whistles through rigging or some other obstacle that cuts it.
W24.
Scission.
WW2.
WWWWW.
The blue WWWWW.
WWW is nine is qualu.
WWW Scission Bleedy W.
There can be no doubt that the Odyssean line was suggested by the Iliadic, but nothing can explain why Idaeus jumping from his chariot should suggest to the writer of the Odyssey the sun jumping from the sea.
The probability is that she never gave the matter a thought, but took the line in question as an effect of saturation with the Iliad and of unconscious cerebration.
The Odyssey contains many such examples.
25.
The heart, liver, lights, kidneys, etc.
were taken out from the inside and eaten first as being more readily cooked.
The greca, or bone meat, was cooking while the Greek or inward parts were being eaten.
I imagine that the thigh bones made a kind of gridiron, while at the same time the marrow inside them got cooked to twenty-six, i.e.
skewers, either single, double, or even five pronged.
The meat would be pierced with the skewer, and laid over the ashes to grill the two ends of the skewer being supported in whatever way convenient.
Meat so cooking may be seen in any eating-house in Smyrna, or any eastern town.
When I rode across the Troad from the Dardanelles to Hisarlik and Mount Ida, I noticed that my dragomen and his men did all our outdoor cooking exactly in the Odissian and Iliadic fashion.
27.
Kiev.
Il.
XVI.
567.
Greek the Odissian lines are.
Greekus 28.
384.
Reading.
Greek 4 Greek.
C.F.
Odd.
I.
186.
Trinine Pyrene.
The geography of the Aegean as above described is correct, but is probably taken from the lost poem The Gnosti, the existence of which is referred to odd.
i.
3026, 3027, and 3050, and c. A glance at the map will show that heaven advised its supplicants quite correctly.
30.
W. Problius, the writer ever jealous for the honor of women, extenuates Clytemnestra's guilt as far as possible, and explains it as due to her having been left unprotected and fallen into the hands of a wicked man.
The Greek is Greek is Greeker CF.
Iliad, i.e.
408 Greek.
Surely the Greek of the Odyssean passage was due to the Greek of the Iliad.
No other reason suggests itself for the making Menelaus return on the very day of the feast given by Orestes.
The fact that in the Iliad Menelaus came to a banquet without waiting for an invitation
determines the writer of the Odyssey to make him come to a banquet, also uninvited, but as circumstances did not permit of his having been invited, his coming uninvited is shown to have been due to chance.
I do not think the author has thought all this out, but attribute the strangeness of the coincidence to unconscious cerebration and saturation.
32.
Sioux Force.
52.
52 force quote ill I 458 to 421 the writer here interrupts an Iliadic passage to which she returns immediately for the double purpose of dwelling upon the slaughter of the heifer and of letting Nestor's wife and daughter enjoy it also a male writer if he was borrowing from the Iliad would have stuck to his borrowing
33 cf ill xx eve 58 7 58 where the lines refer to the washing the dead body of hector 34 see illustration on opposite page the yard is typical of many that may be seen in sicily the existing ground plan is probably unmodified from odyssean and indeed long pre-odyssean times but the earlier buildings would have no arches and would one would suppose be mainly timber
The Odyssean Greek were the sheds that ran round the yard as the arches do now.
The Greek was the one through which the main entrance passed and which was hence noisy or reverberating.
It had an upper story in which visitors were often lodged.
This journey is an impossible one.
Telemachus and Pisistratus would have been obliged to drive over the Tigitus range, over which there has never yet been a road for wheeled vehicles.
It is plain, therefore, that the audience for whom the Odyssey was written was one that would be unlikely to know anything about the topography of the Peloponnese, so that the writer might take what liberties she chose.
The lines which I have enclosed in brackets are evidently an afterthought, added probably by the writer herself, for they evince the same instinctively greater interest in anything that may concern a woman, which is so noticeable throughout the poem.
There is no further sign of any special festivities nor of any other guests than Telemachus and Pisistratus,
until lines 621 to 624, ordinarily enclosed in brackets, are abruptly introduced, probably with a view of trying to carry off the introduction of the lines now in question.
The addition was, I imagine, suggested by a desire to excuse and explain the non-appearance of Hermione in BKW and 60S,
as also of both Hermione and Megapenthes in the rest of BKWence in the rest of BKW.
Megapenthes in BKXV seems to be still a bachelor.
The presumption, therefore, is that BKXV was written before the story of his marriage here given.
I take it he is only married here because his sister is being married.
She having been properly attended to, Megapenthes might as well be married at the same time.
Hermione could not now be less than 30.
I have dealt with this passage somewhat more fully in my Authoress of the Odyssey, p.
136-138.
See also p.
256 of the same book.
1036 of the same book, thus 37 places, though in other parts of the poem it is clear that the writer understands them as one.
The catalogue in the Iliad, which the writer is here presumably following, makes the same mistake, il.
i.e.
581, 582, the 38, the 38.
These last three lines are identical with il.
v.ci.
604-6I6, thus 39-5-4-6I6, it is plain that Menelaus took up the piece of meat with his fingers, Docen 48.
Docen 40ae.
Amber is never mentioned in the Iliad.
Sicily, where I suppose the Odyssey to have been written, has always been, and still is, one of the principal amber-producing countries.
It was probably the only one known in the Odyssean age.
See The Authorus of the Odyssey, Longman's 1898 p186, the 41.
This no doubt refers to the story told in the last poem of the Cypria about Paris and Helen robbing Menelaus of the greater part of his treasures when they sailed together for Troy.
It is inconceivable that Helen should enter thus, in the middle of supper, intending to work with her distaff, if great festivities were going on.
Telemachus and Pisistratus are evidently dining en famille, night 43.
In the Italian insurrection of 1848, eight young men who were being hotly pursued by the Austrian police hid themselves inside Donatello's colossal wooden horse in the Salone at Padua and remained there for a week, being fed by their confederates.
In 1898, the last survivor was carried round Padua in triumph.
The Greek is Greek e. Greek.
Is it unfair to argue that the writer is a person of somewhat delicate sensibility, to whom a strong smell of fish is distasteful?
c4c.
No.
The Greek is Greek.
I believe this to be a hit at the writer's own countrymen who were of Phokian descent, and the next following line to be a rejoinder to complaints made against her in B. K. Phi.
By Phi Phi.
273-288, to the effect that she gave herself heirs and would marry none of her own people.
For that, the writer of the Odyssey was the person who has been introduced into the poem under the name of Nausicaa, I cannot bring myself to question.
I may remind English readers that Greek GGEE Phoka means seal.
Seals almost always appear on Phokian coins.
GG
Sheerly here again, we are in the hands of a writer of delicate sensibility.
It is not as though the seals were stale, they had only just been killed.
The writer, however, is obviously laughing at her own countrymen and insulting them as openly as she dares.
The 47.
We were told above, lines 3056, 3057, that it was only one day's sale.
The 48 manny sale.
I give the usual translation, but I do not believe the Greek will warrant it.
The Greek reads Greek bannis.
This is usually held to mean that Ithaca is an island fit for breeding goats, and on that account more delectable to the speaker than it would have been if it were fit for breeding horses.
I find little authority for such a translation.
The most equitable translation of the text as it stands is, Ithaca is an island fit for breeding goats, and delectable rather than fit for breeding horses, for not one of the islands is good driving ground, nor well meadowed.
Surely the writer does not mean that a pleasant or delectable island would not be fit for breeding horses.
The most equitable translation, therefore, of the present text being thus halt and impotent, we may suspect corruption, and I hazard the following emendation, though I have not adopted it in my translation, as fearing that it would be deemed too fanciful.
I would read, GREEKER.
As far as scanning goes, the GREEKER is not necessary.
GREEKER of 72, footnote GREEKIVE.
233, to go no further afield than earlier lines of the same book, gives sufficient authority for Grieco, but the Grieco would not be redundant, it would emphasize the surprise of the contrast, and I should prefer to have it, though it is not very important either way.
This reading, of course, should be translated.
Ithaca is an island fit for breeding goats, and by your leave itself a horseman rather than fit for breeding horses, for not one of the islands is good and well-meadowed ground.
This would be sure to baffle the Alexandrian editors.
How, they would ask themselves, could an island be a horseman?
And they would cast about for an emendation.
a visit to the top of Mantinechin.
Eryx might perhaps make the meaning intelligible and suggest my proposed restoration of the text to the reader as readily as it did to myself.
I have elsewhere stated my conviction that the writer of the Odyssey was familiar with the old Seacon city at the top of Mantine, Eryx, and that the Aegidean islands which are so striking when seen thence did duty with her for the Ionian islands.
Maretimo, the highest and most westerly of the group, standing for Ithaca.
When seen from the top of Might Eryx, Maretimo shows as it should do according to Ode.
Ix.
25, 26, on the horizon, all highest up in the sea towards the west, while the other islands lie some way off it to the east.
As we descend to Trapani, Maretimo appears to sink on to the top of the island of Lovanzo, behind which it disappears.
My friend, the late Signor Ibiagini, pointed to it once as it was just standing on the top of Lovanzo, and said to me, Come cavalca bene, how well it rides, and this immediately suggested my emendation to me.
Later on, I found in the hymn to the Pythian Apollo, which abounds with tags taken from the Odyssey, a line ending Greek which strengthened my suspicion that this was the original ending of the second of the two lines above under consideration.
See note on line 3 of this book.
The reader will observe that the writer has been unable to keep the women out of an interpolation consisting only of four lines.
50 cell 5 n sheria means a piece of land jutting out into the sea.
In my authorus of the Odyssey, I thought jutland would be a suitable translation, but it has been pointed out to me that jutland only means the land of the jutes.
Irrigation, as here described, is common in gardens near Tripani.
The water that supplies the duts is drawn from wells by a mule, who turns a wheel with buckets on it.
T.O.T.
There is not a word here about the cattle of the sun god.
D.O.T.O.T.
The writer evidently thought the green, growing wood might also be well seasoned.
D.O.T.
54.
The reader will note that the river was flowing with saltwater, i.e.
that it was tidal.
D.O.T.
55.
Diogegean island was not so far off, but that Nauegegean island was not so far off, but that Nauecheatea might be assumed to know where it was.
56.
Greek.
57.
I suspect a family joke, or sly allusion to something of which we know nothing, in this story of Eurymedusa's having been brought from Epirus.
The Greek word Epirus means inexperienced, ignorant.
Is it possible that Eurymedusa was notoriously incompetent?
58-Tus.
Polyphemus was also son to Neptune, see Ode.
Ix.
4212, 52-9.
He was therefore half-brother to Nausethaus, half-uncle to King Alcinus, and half-great-uncle to Nausicaa.
59.
It would seem as though the writer thought that Marathon was close to Athens.
60.
Here, the writer, knowing that she is drawing with embellishments from things actually existing, becomes impatient of past tenses and slides into the present.
This is hidden malice, implying that the Phaeacian magnates were no better than they should be.
The final drink offering should have been made to Jove or Neptune, not to the god of thievishness and rascality of all kinds.
In line 1044, we do indeed find Eceneas proposing that a drink offering should be made to Jove, but Mercury is evidently, according to our authorus, the god who was most likely to be of use to them.
62.
The fact of Alcinous knowing anything about the Cyclopes suggests that in the writer's mind, Sheria and the country of the Cyclopes were not very far from one another.
I take the Cyclopes and the giants to be one and the same people, non-63, non-my property, etc.
The authoress is here adopting an Iliadic line, x6, 333, and this must account for the absence of all reference to Penelope.
If she had happened to remember ill, V213, she would doubtless have appropriated it by preference, for that line reads, my country, my wife, and all the greatness of my house.
NE64, the at first inexplicable sleep of Ulysses BK, Shiite.
79 etc.
is here, as also in VI.
445 being obviously prepared,
The writer evidently attached the utmost importance to it.
Those who know that the harbour which did duty with the writer of the Odyssey, for the one in which Ulysses landed in Ithaca, was only about two miles from the place in which Ulysses is now talking with Alcinous, will understand why the sleep was so necessary.
There were two classes, the lower who were found in provisions which they had to cook for themselves in the yards and outer precincts, where they would also eat, and the upper who would eat in the cloisters of the inner court and have their cooking done for them.
De 66.
Translation very dubious.
I suppose the Greek are here to be the covered sheds that ran round the outer courtyard.
See illustrations at the end of BK.
Iii.
67.
The writer apparently deems that the words, as compared with what oxen can plough in the same time, go without saying.
Not so, the writer of the Iliad, from which the Odyssean passage is probably taken.
He explains that mules can plough quicker than oxen ill.
X.
351-3533.
68.
It was very fortunate that such a disc happened to be there, seeing that none like it were in common use.69 ill69.war
Ill.
Shi'i.
37.
Here, as so often elsewhere in the Odyssey, the appropriation of an Iliadic line, which is not quite appropriate, puzzles the reader.
The they is not the chains, nor yet Mars and Venus.
It is an overflow from the Iliadic passage, in which Neptune hobbles his horses in bonds, which none could either unloose or break, so that they might stay there in that place.
If the line would have scanned without the addition of the words so that they might stay there in that place, they would have been omitted in the Odyssey.
The reader will note that Alcinous never goes beyond saying that he is going to give the goblet, he never gives it.
Elsewhere in both Iliad and Odyssey, the offer of a present is immediately followed by the statement that it was given and received gladly.
Alcinous actually does give a chest and a cloak and shirt, probably also some of the corn and wine for the long two-mile voyage was provided by him, but it is quite plain that he gave no talent and no cup.
Text E24 too.
Text ET E W E E WT WT E WT WT WT
These lines in the Iliad tell of the preparation for washing the body of Patroclus, and I am not pleased that the writer of the Odyssey should have adopted them here.
See note 64.
See note, see note, see note, see note, see note, see note.
The reader will find this threat fulfilled in BK.
She e to 75.
If the other islands lay some distance away from Ithaca, which the word Greek suggests, what becomes of the paraca or gut between Ithaca and Samos, which we hear of in BK's?
I.V.
and X.V.
I suspect that the Orthores in her mind makes Telemachus come back from Pylos to the Lilibane promontory and thence to Trepani through the strait between the Isola Grande and the mainland, the island of Wisteria being the one on which Mortia afterwards stood.
Diss.
76.
AXVI.
E.L.
E.E.XVI.
533, 5334.
The sudden lapse into the third person here for a couple of lines is due to the fact that the two Iliadic lines taken are in the third person.deei.
77, tower, cf.
ill, ei, 776.
The words in both Iliad and Odyssey are footnote Greek.
In the Iliad, they are used of the horses of Achilles' followers as they stood idle, champing lotus.
I take all this passage about the Cyclopes having no ships to be sarcastic, meaning, you people of Drapanum have no excuse for not colonizing the island of Favoniana, which you could easily do, for you have plenty of ships, and the island is a very good one.
For that the island so fully described here is the Aigadian, or Goat, island of Favoniana.
and that the Cyclopes are the old Cycan inhabitants of Mantegna, Erechs should not be doubted.
The Seventy-Nine Four For the reasons why it was necessary that the night should be so exceptionally dark see the authoress of the Odyssey, P. P. A., one-teen-eight, monty-nine, fourteen-eight, mon-pon-fort-nine, fort-nine-fort, monteen-fort-nine, two-thousand-seventy-nine, one-eight, fort-nine-forten,
None but such lambs as would suck if they were with their mothers would be left in the yard.
The older lambs should have been out feeding.
The authoress has got it all wrong, but it does not matter.
81.
This line is enclosed in brackets in the received text, and is omitted with note by Messrs.
Butcher and Lang.
But lines enclosed in brackets are almost always genuine.
All that brackets mean is that the bracketed passage puzzled some early editor, who nevertheless found it too well established in the text to venture on omitting it.
In the present case, the line bracketed is the very last which a full-grown male editor would be likely to interpolate.
It is safer to infer that the writer, a young woman, not knowing or caring at which end of the ship the rudder should be, determined to make sure by placing it at both ends, which we shall find she presently does by repeating it, Lime 3 Fortis, at the stern of the ship.
As for the two rocks thrown, the first I take to be the Assinelli, sea map facing P80.
The second I see is the two contiguous islands of the Formiche, which are treated as one, see map facing P108.
The Assinelli is an island shaped like a boat, and pointing to the island of Favagnana.
I think the authoress's compatriots, who probably did not like her much better that she did them, jeered at the absurdity of Ulysses' conduct, and saw the Assinelli, or donkeys, not as the rock thrown by Polyphemus, but as the boat itself containing Ulysses and his men.
This line exists in the text here, but not in the corresponding passage G.
41.
I am inclined to think it is interpolated, probably by the poetess herself, from the first of lines XI.
1.15.37, which I can hardly doubt were added by the writer when the scheme of the work was enlarged and altered.
See The Authoress of the Odyssey.
PPT.
2054-2055.
2083 all live.
Floating.
2054-2055.
The island itself, as apart from its inhabitants, was quite normal.
There is no indication of its moving during the month that Ulysses stayed with Aeolus, and on his return from his unfortunate voyage, he seems to have found it in the same place.
The Jari, in fact, should no more be pressed than Tharia as applied to islands, Odyssey XV-299, where they are called flying because the ship would fly past them.
So also the Wanderers, as explained by Buttman, see note on Odyssey, see Chai.
S chi y, s chi yi, s chi yi, s chi yi, fifty chi, f chi yi.
84.
Literally, for the ways of the night and of the day are near.
I have seen what Mr. Andrew Lang says, Homer and the Epic, p.
236, and Longman's Magazine for January, 1898, p.
237-7, about the Amber Root and the Sacred Way in this connection.
But until he gives his grounds for holding that the Mediterranean peoples in the Odyssean age used to go far north for their amber, instead of getting it in Sicily, where it is still found in considerable quantities, I do not know what weight I ought to attach to his opinion.
I have been unable to find grounds for asserting that B.C.
1000 there was any commerce between the Mediterranean and the far north, but I shall be very ready to learn if Mr. Lang will enlighten me.
C. The Authoress of the Odyssey, pp 185-86
One would have thought that when the sun was driving the stag down to the water, Ulysses might have observed its whereabouts.
Ulysses might have observed its whereabouts.
Now returnomestits.
See Hobbs of Malmesbury's translation.
87.
Ill.
VXII.
34.9.
Again the writer draws from the washing the body of Patroplus, which offends.
88.X.2.
This visit is wholly without topographical significance.
89.
Brides presented themselves instinctively to the imagination of the writer as the phase of humanity which she found most interesting.
.92 Ulysses was, in fact, to become a missionary and preach Neptune to people who knew not his name.
I was fortunate enough to meet in Sicily a woman carrying one of these winnowing shovels.
It was not much shorter than an oar, and I was able at once to see what the writer of the Odyssey intended.
91S.
I suppose the lines I have enclosed in brackets to have been added by the author when she enlarged her original scheme by the addition of books, I.I.I.V.
and She.I.
from line 07, X.X.I.V.
The reader will observe that in the corresponding passage, C.E.She.
No.
37-14-1 the prophecy ends with, after losing all your comrades, and that there is no allusion to the suitors.
For fuller explanation see The Authoress of the Odyssey pp.
254-255-292-295.
Number Thirst the reader will remember that we are in the first year of Ulysses Wanderings, Telemachus therefore was only 11 years old.
The same anachronism is made later on in this book.
See The Authorus of the Odyssey, pp.
132-133.
Mighty III.
Mighty III, Excebo, C.F.X.
Mighty C.F.
Boe, Odyssey.
Mighty III.
Exfo, F.Foe, Exbo, Expo, F.O.F.
Mighty IV, Al.
not to be confounded with Aeolus, King of the Winds.
95 Boe F. My T.F.
My Lampus.
My Lampus Bull F. Boe F. My have already said in a note on B.K.
I have already said in a note on B.K.
X.I.
I.T.6 that at this point of Ulu 97.
Is the writer a man or a woman?
98 C.F.
ill.
If 5021, Greek.
The Odyssean line reads, Greek.
The famous dactylism, therefore, of the Odyssean line was probably suggested by that of the Iliadic rather than by a desire to accommodate sound to sense.
At any rate, the double coincidence of a dactylic line and an ending Greek seems conclusive as to the familiarity of the writer of the Odyssey with the Iliadic line.
99.
Off the coast of Sicily in South Italy, in the month of May, I have seen men fastened halfway up a boat's mast with their feet resting on a cross-piece, just large enough to support them.
From this point of vantage they spear swordfish.
When I saw men thus employed I could hardly doubt that the writer of the Odyssey had seen others like them and had them in her mind when describing the binding of Ulysses.
I have therefore, with some diffidence, ventured to depart from the received translation of GSEF, Alcaeus-Frag.
18.
Where, however, it is very hard to say what Miastiestiestiestiestiestiestiestiestiestiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiensiens
but I have looked for the passage in vain."
The writer is at fault here and tries to put it off on Circe.
When Ulysses comes to take the route prescribed by Circe, he ought to pass either the Wanderers or some other difficulty of which we are not told, but he does not do so.
The Plankti, or Wanderers, merge into Scylla and Charybdis, and the alternative between them and something untold merges into the alternative whether Ulysses had better choose Scylla or Charybdis.
Yet from line 260, it seems we are to consider the Wanderers as having been passed by Ulysses.
This appears even more plainly from XXI.
327, in which Ulysses expressly mentions the wandering rocks as having been between the Sirens and Scylla and Charybdis.
The writer, however, is evidently unaware that she does not quite understand her own story.
Her difficulty was perhaps due to the fact that though Trapanese sailors had given her a fair idea as to where all her other localities really were, no one in those days more than in our own could localize the planktie, which in fact, as Buttman has argued, were derived not from any particular spot,
but from sailors' tales about the difficulties of navigating the group of the Aeolian Islands as a whole, see note on Odd XXIII.
Still the matter of the poor doves caught her fancy, so she would not forgo them.
The whirlwinds of fire and the smoke that hangs on Scylla suggest allusion to Stromboli and perhaps even Etna.
Scylla is on the Italian side and therefore may be said to look west.
It is about 8 miles thence to the Sicilian coast, so Ulysses may be perfectly well told that after passing Scylla he will come to the Thranacian island or Sicily.
Charybdis is transposed to a site some few miles to the north of its actual position.
I suppose this line to have been intercalated by the author when lines 426-446 were added.
202.
For the reasons which enable us to identify the island of the two sirens with the Lipari island, now Salinas, the ancient Didyme, or Twin Island, see the Authoress of the Odyssey, pp.
95-96.
The two sirens doubtless were, as their name suggests, the whistling gusts, or avalanches of air that at times descend without a moment's warning from the two lofty mountains of Salinas, as also from all high points in the neighborhood.
903T
See Admiral Smith on the Currents in the Straits of Messina, quoted in The Authorus of the Odyssey, p.
97 and 940t.
In the islands of Favognana and Maretimo off Trapani, I have seen men fish exactly as here described.
They chew bread into a paste and throw it into the sea to attract the fish, which they then spear.
No line is used.
903T.
1005.
The writer evidently regards Ulysses as on a coast that looked east at no great distance south of the Straits of Messina, somewhere, say, near Tauromenium, now Taomina.
1006.1.
1006.
Px.
of 1006.
Surely there must be a line missing here to tell us that the keel and mast were carried down into Charybdis.
Besides, the Aorist Greek in, in its present surrounding, is perplexing.
I have translated it as though it were an imperfect, I see messes.
Butcher and Lange translate it as a pluperfect, but surely Charybdis was in the act of sucking down the water when Ulysses arrived.
I suppose the passage within brackets to have been an afterthought but to have been written by the same hand as the rest of the poem.
I suppose Exi, 1003, to have been also added by the writer when she decided on sending Ulysses back to Charybdis.
The simile suggests the hand of the wife or daughter of a magistrate who had often seen her father come in cross and tired.
GRCN.
GRCRC.
GRCR.
G.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.C.R.
A male writer would have made Ulysses say, not, may your wives give satisfaction to you, one one one one.
See note quote 64.
Play important twenty nine one.
See note twenty twenty twenty.
Extermest of quote.
The land was in reality the shallow inlet, now the salt works of S. Cusimano.
the neighborhood of Trepani and Mint Eriks being made to do double duty, both as Sheria and Ithaca.
Hence the necessity for making Ulysses set out after dark, fall instantly into a profound sleep, and wake up on a morning so foggy that he could not see anything till the interviews between Neptune and Jove, and between Ulysses and Minerva, should have given the audience time to accept the situation.
See illustrations and map near the end of BKCC and VIE, respectively.
1011-13 This cave, which is identifiable with singular completeness, is now called the Grotta del Toro, probably a corruption of Tesoro, for it is held to contain a treasure.
See the Authorus of the Odyssey, pp.
1907-1913, 2020-13, 1914-2020,
probably they would.
115 Treibou.
Thereven 15.
Therevou 1115 20.
1116.
Doubtless the road would pass the harbour in Odyssean times, as it passes the saltworks now.
Indeed, if there is to be a road at all, there is no other level ground which it could take.
See map above referred to.
Night 17.
The rock at the end of the northern harbour of Trapani, to which I suppose the writer of the Odyssey to be here referring, still bears the name Malconcilio, the Rock of Evil Council.
There is a legend that it was a ship of Turkish pirates who were intending to attack Trapani, but the Madonna di Trapani crushed them under this rock just as they were coming into port.
My friend Cavaliere Gianni Trapani of Trapani told me that his father used to tell him when he was a boy that if he would drop exactly three drops of oil onto the water near the rock, he would see the ship still at the bottom.
The legend is evidently a Christianized version of the Odyssean story, while the name supplies the additional detail that the disaster happened in consequence of an evil council.
The Fort.
119.
It would seem then that the ship had got all the way back from Ithaca in about a quarter of an hour.
And may we not add, and also to prevent his recognizing that he was only in the place where he had met Nausicaa two days earlier.
220.
All this is to excuse the entire absence of Minerva from books XWY, XWYN, which XWYN, which XWYN, which XWY'd Minerva before the authoress had determined on making Minerva so prominent a character.
21.
We have met with this somewhat lame attempt to cover the writer's change of scheme at the end of BK.
VU 22.
I take the following from The Authoress of the Odyssey.
P.
27.
1007.
It is clear from the text that there were two caves.
Not one, but someone has enclosed in brackets the two lines in which the second cave is mentioned,
I presume because he found himself puzzled by having a second cave sprung upon him, when up to this point he had only been told of one.
I venture to think that if he had known the ground he would not have been puzzled, for there are two caves, distant about eighty or one hundred yards from one another.
The cave in which Ulysses hid his treasure is, as I have already said, identifiable with singular completeness.
The other cave presents no special features, neither in the poem nor in nature.
12.30.
There is no attempt to disguise the fact that Penelope had long given encouragement to the suitors.
The only defense set up is that she did not really mean to encourage them.
Would it not have been wiser to have tried a little discouragement?
1240.
Seamap near the end of BK.
V. B.E.E.
V.E.E.
Rukazu de Ikorvi.
Of course means The Rock of the Ravens.
Both name and ravens still exist.
1205.
Manasi.
The Authoress of the Odyssey.
P.P.
Wanasi.
140 Wanasi.
The real reason for sending Telemachus to Pylos and Lacedaemon was that the Authoress might get Helen of Troy into her poem.
He was sent at the only point in the story at which he could be sent, so he must have gone then, or not at all.
12106, Thousing Chamity Seas, the site I assigned to Eumaeus' hut, close to the Irukazide Corvi, is about 2,000 feet above the sea and commands an extensive view.
1227.
Sandals, such as Eumaeus was making, are still worn in the Abruzzi and elsewhere.
An oblong piece of leather forms the sole, holes are cut at the four corners, and through these holes, leathern straps are passed, which are bound round the foot and cross-guarded of the calf.
W287T, W287TS, W22, 12 mine both, W2292, Telemachus, like many another good young man, seems to expect everyone to fetch and carry for him, W288.
Ill, Vi, 288.
The storeroom was fragrant because it was made of cedar wood.
See Ill, XXX, W22, 92, W289, and 293, 296.
The dress was kept at the bottom of the chest as one that would only be wanted on the greatest occasions.
But surely the marriage of Hermione and of Megapenthe's EPK-EV4-OV10, Ini, might have induced Helen to wear it on the preceding evening, in which case it could hardly have got back.
We find no hint here of Megapenthe's recent marriage.
WSEVR32.
WC NOTE 83W242.
W. W. W2.
W. W2.
Mines 134, the names Syra and Ortigia, on which island a great part of the Doric Syracuse was originally built, suggest that even in Odyssean times there was a prehistoric Syracuse, the existence of which was known to the writer of the poem.
35.
Literally, where are the turnings of the sun?
Assuming, as we may safely do,
that the Syra and Ortigia of the Odyssey refer to Syracuse, it is the fact that not far to the south of these places the land turned sharply round, so that mariners following the coast would find the sun upon the other side of their ship, to that on which they'd had it hitherto.
Mr. A. S. Griffith has kindly called my attention to Herod I.
42, where, speaking of the circumnavigation of Africa by Phoenician mariners under Nekos, he writes,
On their return they declared, I for my part do not believe them, but perhaps others may, that in sailing round Libya, i.e.
Africa, they had the sun upon their right hand.
In this way was the extent of Libya first discovered.
I take it that Eumaeus was made to have come from Syracuse because the writer thought she rather ought to have made something happen at Syracuse during her account of the voyages of Ulysses.
She could not, however, break his long drift from Charybdis to the island of Pantelaria.
She therefore resolved to make it up to Syracuse in another way.
Modern excavations established the existence of two and only two pre-Dorian communities at Syracuse.
They were, so Dr. Orsi informed me, at Plamirio and Coso Pantano.
See The Authoress of the Odyssey pp.
211-212-113, Dora 13-2, Duan 13-13, Doros Duan 113 Kopyu Dorian.
The Harbour that is now the Salt Works of S. Kusumano, 237.
This never can have been anything but very niggardly pay for some eight or nine days' service.
I suppose the crew were to consider the pleasure of having had a trip to Pylos as a set-off.
There is no trace of the dinner as having been actually given, either on the following or any other morning.
SUTHERTEEN 8.
NO HAWK CAN TEAR ITS PREY WHILE IT IS ON THE WING.
SUTHERTEEN 9.
EACH 29.
THE TEXT IS HERE APPARENTLY CORRUPT AND WILL NOT MAKE SENSE AS IT STANDS.
I FOLLOW MESSERS.
BUTCHER AND LANG IN EMITTING LINE 21.
149.
TESCHEN 49.
ET 949.
I.E.
TO BE MILKED AS IN SOUTH ITALIAN AND SICILIAN TOWNS OF THE PRESENT DAY.
TO111.
The butchering and making ready the carcasses took place partly in the outer yard and partly in the open part of the inner court.
Tier 1111.
Tier 111111.
These words cannot mean that it would be afternoon soon after they were spoken.
Ulysses and Eumaeus reached the town which was some way off, Exbiae.
Twenty-five in time for the suitor's early meal, Exbiae.
Seventy-o and one-sixth Eumaeus conjured seventy-sixth say at ten or eleven o'clock.
The context of the rest of the book shows this.
Eumaeus and Ulysses therefore cannot have started later than eight or nine,
and Eumaeus' words must be taken as an exaggeration for the purpose of making Ulysses bestir himself.
I imagine the fountain to have been somewhere about where the church of the Madonna di Trapani now stands, and to have been fed with water from what is now called the Fontana di Fali on Mantierix.
244.
From this and other passages in the Odyssey, it appears that we are in an age anterior to the use of coined money, an age when cauldrons, tripods, swords, cattle, chattels of all kinds, measures of corn, wine, or oil, etc.,
etc.
not to say pieces of gold, silver, bronze, or even iron, wrought more or less, but unstamped, were the nearest approach to a currency that had as yet been reached.
245.
G. Carr.
246.
I correct these proofs abroad, and am not within reach of Hesiod, but surely this passage suggests acquaintance with the works and ways, though it by no means compels it.
247.
It would seem as though Eurynome and Eurycleia were the same person.
See note 156-148.
It is plain, therefore, that Iris was commonly accepted as the messenger of the gods, though our authoress will never permit her to fetch or carry for anyone.
149.
Tafy 5-0-S.
See note 156 Canast T. E5-I 5-0-1.
These, I imagine, must have been in the open part of the inner courtyard, where the maids also stood, and threw the light of their torches into the covered cloister that ran all round it.
The smoke would otherwise have been intolerable.
Translation very uncertain.
Very uncertain.
Biddy Liddell and Scott.
Under Greek and 53.
See photo on opposite page.
23.
Can STF.
Ill, I.I., T4 and 217, 2018.
An additional and well-marked feature being wanted to convince Penelope, the writer has taken the hunched shoulders of Thursites, who is mentioned immediately after Euripides in the Iliad, and put them on to Euripides' back.
This is how geese are now fed in Sicily, at any rate in summer, when the grass is all burnt up.
I have never seen them grazing.
2d Alsa 6, might 24.
Lower down, line 43.
Eurycleia says it was herself that had thrown the cloak over Ulysses, for the plural should not be taken as implying more than one person.
The writer is evidently still fluctuating between Eurycleia and Eurynemy as the name for the old nurse.
She probably originally meant to call her Euryclea, but finding it not immediately easy to make Euryclea scan an XVI, 495, she hastily called her Urinami, intending either to alter this name later, or to change the earlier Eurycleas into Urinami.
She then drifted into Eurynome as convenience further directed, still nevertheless hankering after Eurycleia, till at last she found that the path of least resistance would lie in the direction of making Eurynome and Eurycleia two persons, therefore in XXII.
289-292 both Eurynome and the nurse, who can be none other than Eurycleia, come on together.
I do not say that this is feminine, but it is not unfeminine.
T.S.
5-7.
C.N.
566.
T.S.
5-C-8.
1591.
This is the only allusion to Sardinia in either Iliad or Odyssey.
The normal translation of the Greek word would be holding back, curbing, restraining, but I cannot think that the writer meant this.
She must have been using the word in its other sense of having, holding, keeping, maintaining, W161-92.
I have vainly tried to realize the construction of the fastening here described.
W162 and INT2.
WC.
See plan of Ulysses' house in the appendix.
It is evident that the open part of the court had no flooring but the natural soil.
QM23.
See plan of Ulysses' house and note 175.
QM225.
QM22225.
QM2.
These P2-225, the little table that was set for Ulysses, this was.
C2-222.
Ode.
XX.
Cumint5-9.
Surely the difficulty of this passage has been overrated.
I suppose the iron part of the axe to have been wedged into the handle, or bound securely to it, the handle being half buried in the ground.
The axe would be placed edgeways towards the archer, and he would have to shoot his arrow through the hole into which the handle was fitted when the axe was in use.
Twelve axes were placed in a row all at the same height, all exactly in front of one another, all edgeways to Ulysses whose arrow passed through all the holes from the first onward.
I cannot see how the Greek can bear any other interpretation, the words being Greekic.
He did not miss a single hole from the first onwards.
Greek Acre, according to Liddell and Scott, being the hole for the handle of an axe, etc., while Greek Acre, Acre Obedic, Reek Acre Odd, V236, is, according to the same authorities, the handle itself.
The feat is absurdly impossible, but our authoress sometimes has a soul above impossibilities.
S-66 Probiliu.
The reader will note how the spoiling of good food distresses the writer even in such a supreme moment as this.
S-67 W. Here we have it again.
Waste of substance comes first.
168 Probiliu, 68 W.C.F.
Ill.
I.I.
337 and three other places.
It is strange that the author of the Iliad should find a little horsehair so alarming.
Possibly enough she was merely borrowing a common form line from some earlier poet or poetess, for this is a woman's line rather than a man's.
6920 Gnome.
Or perhaps simply window.
See plan in the appendix.
170. i.e.
the pavement on which Ulysses was standing.
The interpretation of lines.
The interpretation of lines 126-43 is most dubious, and at best we are in a region of melodrama, CF, however, I-425, etc., from which it appears that there was a tower in the outer court, and that Telemachus used to sleep in it.
The cumbershoe, if I take to be a door, or trapdoor, leading on to the roof above Telemachus' bedroom, which we are told was in a place that could be seen from all round, or it might be simply a window in Telemachus' room, looking out into the street.
From the top of the tower, the outer world was to be told what was going on.
But people could not get in by the Taimasa'ing jaan.
They would have to come in by the main entrance.
and Melanthius explains that the mouth of the narrow passage, which was in the lands of Ulysses and his friends, commanded the only entrance by which help could come, so that there would be nothing gained by raising an alarm.
As for the seatory of line 143, no commentator ancient or modern has been able to say what was intended, but whatever they were, Melanthius could never carry twelve shields, twelve helmets, and twelve spears.
Moreover, where he could go, the others could go also.
If a dozen suitors had followed Melanthius into the house, they could have attacked Ulysses in the rear, in which case, unless Minerva had intervened promptly, the odyssey would have had a different ending.
But throughout the scene, we are in a region of extravagance rather than of true fiction.
It cannot be taken seriously by any but the very serious, until we come to the episode of Phemius and Medon, where the writer begins to be at home again.
Trescent 72.
I presume it was intended that there should be a hook driven into the bearing post.
Trescent 73.
What for?
Gr.
Greca.
This is not Dreca.
To 75.
to 75 from lines 33 3 and 3 45 and lines 145 and 146 of bk xxi we can locate the approach to the a greek with some certainty dot and 76 but in xis
500-502 Ulysses scolded Eurycleia for offering information on this very point, and declared himself quite able to settle it for himself.
That 177.
7.
6 doors.
Dolly 78.
Lord Grimthorpe, whose understanding does not lend itself to easy imposition, has been good enough to write to me about my conviction that the Odyssey was written by a woman,
and to send me remarks upon the gross absurdity of the incident here recorded.
It is plain that all the authoress cared about was that the women should be hanged.
As for attempting to realize, or to make her readers realize, how the hanging was done, this was of no consequence.
The reader must take her word for it and ask no questions.
Lord Grimthorpe wrote, I had better send you my ideas about Nausicaa's hanging of the maids, not maidens, of whom Frood wrote so well in his Science of History before I forget it all.
Luckily for me, Liddell and Scott have specially translated most of the doubtful words referring to this very place.
A ship's cable.
I don't know how big a ship she meant, but it must have been a very small one indeed, if its cables could be used to tie tightly round a woman's neck, and still more round a dozen of them in a row, besides being strong enough to hold them and pull them all up.
A dozen average women would need the weight and strength of more than a dozen strong, heavy men, even over the best pulley hung to the roof over them, and the idea of pulling them up by a rope hung anyhow round a pillar,
Greek is absurdly impossible, and how a dozen of them could be hung dangling round one post is a problem which a senior wrangler would be puzzled to answer.
She had better have let Telemachus use his sword as he had intended till she changed his mind for him.
1919.
1999.
1990.
Then they had all been in Ulysses' service over twenty years.
Perhaps the twelve guilty ones had been engaged more recently.
.d.d.c.
I.91.
The Translation Very Doubtful C.F.
It.
XXIF 5981.
281.
But why could she not at once ask to see the scar, of which Eurycleia had told her, or why could not Ulysses have shown it to her?
INT2 Tour.
The people of Ithaca seem to have been as fond of carping as the Phaeacians were in V.
273 Etc.
Ecaeacians were in VIT3.
CNode 83.
Campound.
Ulysses's bedroom does not appear to have been upstairs, nor yet quite within the house.
Is it possible that it was the domed room round the outside of which the erring-maids were, for aught we have heard to the contrary, still hanging?
WNT4.
Ulysses' bedroom in the mind of the writer is here, too, apparently downstairs.
Wenty-five Wenty-five, Wenty-five, Penelope having been now sufficiently whitewashed, disappears from the poem.
Chee-see-see-see's.
Chee-see-see-see-see's.
So practice to wash a woman, as our authoress doubtless knew that, by this time, the web must have become such a wreck that it would have gone to pieces in the wash.
A lady points out to me, just as these sheets are leaving my hands, that no really good needlewoman, no one, indeed, whose work or character was worth consideration, could have endured, no matter for what reason, the unpicking of her day's work, day after day, for between three and four years.
Titodi.
We must suppose Dolius not yet to know that his son Melanthius had been tortured, mutilated, and left to die by Ulysses' orders on the preceding day, and that his daughter Melantho had been hanged.
Dolius was probably exceptionally simple-minded, and his name was ironical.
So, on my Tidrix, the first-of-first-of-first-of-firstie, was called Sonsa Malacia, or Guiless, he being held exceptionally cunning.
END of the Project Gutenberg.
E-book.
The Odyssey Assist's updated editions will replace the previous one.
The old editions will be renamed.
Creating the works from print editions not protected by US copyright law means that no one owns a United States copyright in these works, so the Foundation and you can copy and distribute it in the United States without permission and without paying copyright royalties.
Special rules set forth in the general terms of use part of this license
Apply to copying and distributing Project Gutenbergi electronic works to protect the PROJECT Gutenbergi concept and trademark.
Project Gutenberg is a registered trademark and may not be used if you charge for an e-book, except by following the terms of the trademark license, including paying royalties for use of the Project Gutenberg trademark.
If you do not charge anything for copies of this e-book, complying with the trademark license is very easy.
You may use this e-book for nearly any purpose such as creation of derivative works, reports, performances and research.
Project Gutenberg e-books may be modified and printed and given away.
You may do practically anything in the United States with e-books not protected by US copyright law.
Redistribution is subject to the trademark license, especially commercial redistribution.
Start full license the full project.
Gutenberg license please.
Read this before you distribute or use this work to protect the Project Gutenberg and mission of promoting the free distribution of electronic works by using or distributing this work
or any other work associated in any way with the phrase Project Gutenberg, you agree to comply with all the terms of the full Project Gutenberger license available with this file or online at license available with this file or online at www.gutenberg.org's license.
Section 1.
General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project Gutenbergi Electronic Works 1a.
By reading or using any part of this project Gutenbergi Electronic Work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agreed to and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property trademark copyright agreement.
If you do not agree to abide by all the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or destroy all copies of Project Gutenbergi electronic works in your possession.
If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a Project Gutenbergi electronic work,
and you do not agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the person or entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph 1W82, 1W8, 1W8, 1W8.
Project Gutenberg is a registered trademark.
It may only be used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement.
There are a few things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg electronic works even without complying with the full terms of this agreement.
See paragraph 1c below.
There are a lot of things you can do with Project Gutenberg electronic works if you follow the terms of this agreement and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg electronic works.
See paragraph 1e below.
1C, the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the Foundation, or PGLAF, owns a compilation copyright in the collection of Project Gutenberg electronic works.
Nearly all the individual works in the collection are in the public Domerg Electronic Works.
Nearly all the individual works in the collection are in the public domain in the United States.
If an individual work is unprotected by copyright law in the United States, and you are located in the United States, we do not claim a right to prevent you from copying, distributing, performing, displaying or creating derivative works based on the work as long as all references to Project Gutenberg are removed.
Of course, we hope that you will support the Project Gutenbergen mission of promoting free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project Gutenbergen works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for keeping the Project Gutenbergen name associated with the work.
You can easily comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the same format with its attached full Project Gutenbergen license when you share it without charge with others.
1d.
The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern what you can do with this work.
Copyright laws in most countries are in a constant state of change.
If you are outside the United States, check the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this agreement, before downloading, copying, displaying, performing, distributing or creating derivative works based on this work or any other Project Gutenbergen work.
The Foundation makes no representations concerning the copyright status of any work in any country other than the United States.
1e.
Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg, 1e.1.
The following sentence.
With active links to, or other immediate access to, the full Project Gutenberg-y license must appear prominently,
Whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg-y work, any work on which the phrase Project Gutenberg appears, or with which the phrase Project Gutenberg is associated, is accessed, displayed, performed, viewed, copied, or distributed, this e-book is for the use of anyone, anywhere in the United States, and most other parts of the world, at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever.
You may copy it, give it away, or reuse it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg license included with this e-book or online at www.gutenberg.org.
If you are not located in the United States, you will have to check the laws of the country where you are located before using this e-book.
1.e2 If an individual Project Gutenbergel electronic work is derived from texts not protected by US copyright law,
does not contain a notice indicating that it is posted with permission of the copyright holder.
The work can be copied and distributed to anyone in the United States without paying any fees or charges.
If you are redistributing or providing access to a work with the phrase Project Gutenberg associated with or appearing on the work,
you must comply either with the requirements of paragraphs 1W1 through 1W1 through 1W1, W1 through 1W1W1, W1W7 or obtain permission for the use of the work and the Project Gutenbergi trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1W1W1, 1E3.
If an individual Project Gutenbergi electronic work is posted with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution must comply with both paragraphs 1d1 through 1d7 and any additional terms imposed by the copyright holder.
Additional terms will be linked to the Project Gutenbergi license for all works posted with the permission of the copyright holder found at the beginning of this work.
1D4.
Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberger license terms from this work or any files containing a part of this work.
or any other work associated with Project Gutenberg-Elias.
1e5.
Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph 1e1,
with active links or immediate access to the full terms of the Project Gutenberger License 1e6.
You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary, compressed, marked-up, non-proprietary or proprietary form, including any word processing or hypertext form.
However, if you provide access to or distribute copies of a Project Gutenberger work in a format other than plain vanilla ASCII, or other format used in the official version posted on the official Project Gutenberger website, www.gutenberger.org,
You must, at no additional cost, fee or expense to the user, provide a copy, a means of exporting a copy or a means of obtaining a copy, upon request, of the work in its original, plain vanilla ASCII or other form.
Any alternate format must include the full Project Gutenbergi license as specified in paragraph 1T1.
1T1, 1T7.
Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying, performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg eWorks unless you comply with paragraph 1T8 or 1T9.
1T8.
You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of,
or providing access to or distributing Project Gutenberg-y electronic works, provided that you pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from the use of Project Gutenberg-y works, calculated using the method you already use to calculate your applicable taxes.
The fee is owed to the owner of the Project Gutenberg-an trademark, but he has agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.
Royalty payments must be paid within 60 days following each date on which you prepare, or are legally required to prepare, your periodic tax returns.
Royalty payments should be clearly marked as such and sent to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the address specified in Section 4, information about donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.
You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies you in writing, you or by email, within 30 days of receipt that Skihi does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberger license.
You must require such a user to return or destroy all copies of the works possessed in a physical medium and discontinue all use of and all access to other copies of Project Gutenberger works.
You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.if3, a full refund of any money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days of receipt of the work.
You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free distribution of Project Gutenberger works.
1.e9 If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project Gutenberger electronic work or group of works on different terms than are set forth in this agreement,
You must obtain permission in writing from the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the manager of the Project Gutenberger Trademark.
Contact the Foundation as set forth in Section 3 below.
1.1.
IF ONE Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread works not protected by U.S.
copyright law in creating the Project Gutenberg collection.
Despite these efforts, Project Gutenbergi electronic works and the medium on which they may be stored may contain defects such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.
1wc limited warranty disclaimer of damages except for the right of replacement or refund described in paragraph 1 tf3 the project gutenberg literary archive foundation the owner of the project gutenberg e trademark
and any other party distributing a Project Gutenberg electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal fees.
You agree that you have no remedies for negligence, strictly ability, breach of warranty or breach of contract.
except those provided in paragraph 143.
You agree that the foundation, the trademark owner, and any distributor under this agreement will not be liable to you for actual, direct, indirect, consequential, punitive, or incidental.
Direct, indirect, consequential, punitive, or incidental.
Damages even if you give notice of the possibility of segligence, straitligence, strict liability, negligence, prementia.
Limited right of replacement or refund.
If you discover a defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money, if any, you paid for it, by sending a written explanation to the person you received the work from.
If you received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium with your written explanation.
The person or entity that provided you with the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in lieu of a refund.
If you received the work electronically, the person or entity providing it to you may choose to give you a second opportunity to receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund.
If the second copy is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing without further opportunities to fix the problem.
1.
F Topi 4.
Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth in paragraph 1.of 3, this work is provided to you, A.S.
Isses, with no other warranties of any kind, express or impleed, including but not limited to warranties of merchantability or fitness for any purpose.
1.5.
Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain implied warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of damages.
If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement violates the law of the state applicable to this agreement, the agreement shall be interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or limitation permitted by the applicable state law.
The invalidity or unenforceability of any provision of this Agreement shall not void the remaining provisions.
1 Port Fort 46 Indemnity.
You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone providing copies of Project Gutenbergi electronic works in accordance with this Agreement,
and any volunteers associated with the production, promotion and distribution of Project Gutenbergi electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs and expenses, including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of the following, which you do or cause to occur, or key distribution of this or any Project Gutenbergi work, alteration, modification or additions or deletions to any Project Gutenbergi work, and or key any defect you cause,
Section 2 Information about the mission of Project Gutenberger Project Gutenberger is synonymous with the free distribution of electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of computers including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers.
It exists because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations from people in all walks of life.
Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the assistance they need are critical to reaching Project Gutenberger's goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberger collection will remain freely available for generations to come.
In 2001, the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure and permanent future for Project Gutenberger and future generations.
To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations can help, see Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation information page at www.org.
Section 3 Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation
The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non-profit 501-623 educational corporation organized under the laws of the state of Mississippi and granted tax-exempt status by the Internal Revenue Service.
The Foundation's EIN, or Federal Tax Identification Number, is 64-622-1541.
Contributions to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation
are tax-deductible to the full extent permitted by U.S.
federal laws and your state's laws.
The Foundation's business office is located at 809 North 1500 West, Salt Lake City, UT 805116, Seidman.CIS 1801, 1596-1887.
Email contact links and up-to-date contact information can be found at the Foundation's website and official page at www.gunntact.com Information about donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation project, Gutenbergi, depends upon and cannot survive without widespread public support and donations to carry out its mission of increasing the number of public domain
and licensed works that can be freely distributed in machine-readable form, accessible by the widest array of equipment, including outdated equipment.
Many small donations, 1 to 5,000, are particularly important to maintaining tax-exempt status with the IRS.
The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United States.
Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up with these requirements.
We do not solicit donations in locations where we have not received written confirmation of compliance.
to send donations or determine the status of compliance for any particular state visit www.doc.orgs.nl While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who approach us with offers to donate.
International donations are gratefully accepted,
but we cannot make any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from outside the United States.
U.S.
laws alone swamp our small staff.
Please check the Project Gutenberg webpages for current donation methods and addresses.
Donations are accepted in a number of other ways, including checks, online payments and credit card donations.
To donate, please visit www.gutenberg.org.au.
Section 5.
General Information About Project Gutenbergi Electronic Works Professor Michael S. Hart was the originator of the Project Gutenbergi concept of a library of electronic works that could be freely shared with anyone.
For 40 years, he produced and distributed Project Gutenbergian e-books with only a loose network of volunteer support.
Project Gutenbergene e-books are often created from several printed editions, all of which are confirmed as not protected by copyright in the US, unless a copyright notice is included.
Thus, we do not necessarily keep e-books in compliance with any particular paper edition.
Most people start at our website, which has the main PG search facility www.pgsearch.org.
This website includes information about Project Gutenbergi, including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new e-books, and how to subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new e-books.