PROLOGUE - FROM THE FALL OF TROY TO THE RETURN HOME. The great flood of Greek history that is the Odyssey begins not with a wind in the sea or an omen on the shore, but with a man who has been missing for 21 years and the world he left behind.
To hear the tale as it unfolds you must first understand how Troy fell, why the Greeks had to leave their homes for so long, and what happened during those years of wandering that made Odysseus' homecoming an epic in its own right.
THE SEIGE THAT NEVER ENDED
In the Iliad, we are taken into the heart of a war that began with a single spark, the abduction or elopement of Helen, Queen of Sparta, by Paris of Troy.
A thousand heroes, each bearing their own grievances and glory, were drawn into a conflict that would last ten years.
The Greeks, or Achaeans as Homer called them, besieged the city of Ilium for almost a decade, but the war never truly ended until the cunning use of the Trojan horse.
The horse was not a simple trick.
It was an act of deception born from frustration and exhaustion.
The Greek army had tried to break Troy's walls by force, then by fire, then by stealth.
All failed.
Odysseus, who would become famous for his cunning later on, devised a wooden horse that could hold a small group of warriors inside.
He left it at the gates, pretending it was a gift to the goddess Athena and a sign of Greek surrender.
The Trojans, eager to believe they had won, hauled the horse into their city.
Inside, the Greeks waited for nightfall.
When the Trojans celebrated their apparent victory, the Greek soldiers leapt from the horse, opened the gates, and let the rest of the army in.
With fire and slaughter, Troy fell.
THE AFTERMATH - WHY THE HOMECOMING TOOK YEARS. The Greeks had won the war, but they did not win an easy return home.
Several forces conspired to delay their journey-the curse of Poseidon.
In the Iliad, it is made clear that the sea god was displeased with Odysseus for blinding his son Polyphemus the Cyclops.
Poseidon's wrath would follow him all the way back to Ithaca, the divine displeasure of Athena.
Though she aided Odysseus in Troy, Athena was also angry when he killed her beloved son, Hephaestus' son, and at other points, she withheld assistance from the Greeks until they had learned humility.
she would test him again on his way home.
THE WANDERINGS OF THE GREEK SHIPS.
The fleet that left Troy was not a single cohesive unit, but dozens of ships with different commanders, each carrying their own desires for treasure and glory.
Some fell to disaster, others were taken by storms or plagues.
THE POLITICAL TURMOIL.
Back Home In Ithaca, Odysseus' wife Penelope was being courted by suitors who believed he had died or at least would not return in time.
Their presence was a constant reminder that the Greeks could never simply leave their homes behind.
they had to return and reclaim what was theirs.
These forces combined to make the journey home, one of the most famous adventures in Western literature, a long, perilous, and often humiliating trek across the Mediterranean, a test of character, patience, and cunning.
THE FIRST YEARS AFTER TROY. After the fall of Troy, the Greeks began their voyage.
They left from the city of Mycenae, or sometimes from Pylos, depending on later accounts.
The ships were laden with spoils—gold, silver, fine cloth, and other treasures that had been taken from the Trojans.
Odysseus commanded one of these ships.
His crew was a mix of seasoned veterans and younger warriors eager to return home.
The first part of their journey is largely described in Odyssey Book 1, the storm sent by Athena, not Poseidon, as punishment for Odysseus' earlier misdeeds.
The storm wrecks the ship, killing almost everyone on board except Odysseus and his son Telemachus.
They find themselves stranded on a small island, Ogygia home to the nymph Calypso.
CALYPSO'S ISLAND. Calypso, a daughter of the Titan Atlas, keeps Odysseus captive for seven years, offering him immortality in exchange for his companionship.
He is forced to live among her and her people, a quiet yet oppressive existence where he dreams of home but has no hope of leaving.
During these years, Telemachus grows from a boy into a young man under the guidance of Athena disguised as Mentor.
He learns about his father's adventures and begins to question why all the suitors have been so bold in occupying his mother's house.
The tension is building.
Telemachus must take action before Odysseus returns.
THE DEVIND INTERVENTION
The gods are not passive observers, they actively shape the course of events.
In the Odyssey, several deities play pivotal roles, Athena.
She is Odysseus' patron, guiding his journey and encouraging Telemachus to seek knowledge.
Athena sends messages in disguise to both Odysseus, in the form of the wind that brings him back, and Telemachus, Eos, as mentor.
POSEIDON.
He remains angry and actively tries to stop Odysseus' return.
His wrath manifests as storms, monstrous creatures, and obstacles on land.
HERMES.
The messenger god helps Odysseus by providing the instructions that allow him to escape from Calypso's island.
THE FATES.
They decide how long Odysseus will remain captive, ensuring his story unfolds with a sense of destiny.
A WORLD IN TRANSITION.
Between Troy and Ithaca, Greek society itself was changing.
The war had taken away a generation.
Many cities were left empty or reduced to ruins.
The heroes who returned were no longer the same men they were when they left.
Their experiences altered them, some grew wise, others bitter, and many lost their minds entirely.
In this context, Odysseus' return is not just a personal journey but a cultural one.
He must reclaim his throne, restore order to Ithaca, and remind everyone that the Greeks are still capable of cunning and bravery.
His story also serves as a cautionary tale about hubris, how pride can lead to downfall, and the importance of perseverance.
THE STRUCTURE OF THE ODYSSEY. The Odyssey is structured around three main phases.
The Journey Home, Books 2-12 detail Odysseus' Encounters, The Sycones, The Lotus Eaters, The Cyclops Polyphemus, Aeolus the Wind God, The Lacedragonians, Circe, The Sirens, Scylla and Charybdis, The Island of Calypso, and finally his arrival at Ithaca.
The Homecoming, Books 13-16 describe how Odysseus disguises himself as a beggar to assess the situation in his palace, his reunion with Telemachus, and the plan to defeat the suitors.
The Final Reckoning, Books 17-24 focus on the battle against the suitors, the involvement of Athena's disguised form now fully revealed, and Odysseus's ultimate restoration as king of Ithaca.