CHAPTER XXXVI THE QUARTER-DECK ENTER AHAB THEN ALL It was not a great while after the affair of the pipe that one morning shortly after breakfast Ahab, as was his wont, ascended the cabin gangway to the deck.
There most sea-captains usually walk at that hour, as country gentlemen, after the same meal, take a few turns in the garden.
Soon his steady ivory stride was heard, as to and fro he paced his old rounds, upon planks so familiar to his tread, that they were all overdented, like geological stones, with the peculiar mark of his walk.
Did you fixedly gaze, too, upon that ribbed and dented brow there also, you would see still stranger footprints, the footprints of his one unsleeping, ever-pacing thought.
But on the occasion in question, those dents looked deeper, even as his nervous step that morning left a deeper mark.
And, so full of his thought was Ahab, that at every uniform turn that he made, now at the main-mast and now at the binnacle, you could almost see that thought turn in him as he turned, and pace in him as he paced, so completely possessing him, indeed, that it all but seemed the inward mould of every outer movement.
"'Thy mark and flask,' whispered Stubb.
"'The chick that's in him packs the shell.
It will soon be out.'
The hours wore on Ahab now shut up within his cabin, on pacing the deck, with the same intense bigotry of purpose in his aspect.
It drew near the close of day.
Suddenly he came to a halt by the bulwarks, and, inserting his bone leg into the auger-hole there, and with one hand grasping a shroud, he ordered Starbuck to send everybody aft.
"'Sir,' said the mate, astonished at an order seldom or never given on shipboard except in some extraordinary case.
"'Send everybody aft,' repeated Ahab.
"'Mastheads, there, come down!'
When the entire ship's company were assembled, and with curious and not wholly unapprehensive faces,
were eyeing him, for he looked not unlike the weather horizon when a storm is coming up.
Ahab, after rapidly glancing over the bulwarks, and then darting his eyes among the crew, started from his standpoint, and, as though not a soul were nigh him, resumed his heavy turns upon the deck.
With bent head and half-slouched hat he continued to pace, unmindful of the wandering, whispering among the men, till Stubb cautiously whispered to Flask that Ahab must have summoned them there for the purpose of witnessing a pedestrian feat.
But this did not last long.
Vehemently pausing, he cried, cold.
What do ye do when ye see a whale-man sing out for him?
was the impulsive rejoinder from a score of clubbed voices.
Good, cried Ahab, with a wild approval in his tones, observing the hardy animation into which his unexpected question had so magnetically thrown them.
And what do ye next, men?
Lower away, and after him.
And what tune is it ye pole to, men?
A dead whale or a stove-boat?"
Lorne, more strangely and fiercely glad and approving, grew the countenance of the old men at every shout, while the mariners began to gaze curiously at each other, as if marvelling how it was that they themselves became so excited at such seemingly purposeless questions.
But they were all eagerness again, as Ahab, now half-revolving in his pivot-hole, with one hand reaching high up a shroud and tightly, almost convulsively grasping it, addressed them thus, quote, All ye mastheaders have before now heard me give orders about a white whale.
Look ye!
D. A. C. this Spanish ounce of gold?
Holding up a broad, bright coin to the sonnet,
Is a sixteen-dollar piece, men.
D'ye see it?
Mr. Starbuck, hand me on Top Mall."
While the mate was getting the hammer, Ahab, without speaking, was slowly rubbing the gold piece against the skirts of his jacket, as if to heighten its luster.
And without using any words was meanwhile lowly humming to himself, producing a sound so strangely muffled and inarticulate that it seemed the mechanical humming of the wheels of his vitality in him.
Receiving the top maul from Starbuck, he advanced towards the main-mast, with the hammer uplifted in one hand, exhibiting the gold with the other, and with a high-raised voice exclaiming, Whosoever of ye raises me a white-headed whale, with a wrinkled brow and a crooked jaw, and whose woe of ye raises me that white-headed whale, with three holes punctured in his starbur fluke-look ye, whosoever of ye raises me that same white whale, he shall have this gold ounce, my boys.
"'Huzzah!
huzzah!'
cried the seamen, as with swinging tarpaulins they hailed the act of nailing the gold to the mast.
"'It's a white whale, I say,' resumed Ahab, as he threw down the top malco, a white whale.
"'Skin your eyes for him.
Men look sharp for white water.
If he see but a bubble, sing out!'
All this while Tash Tego, Dagoo, and Kwee Kweg had looked on with even more intense interest and surprise than the rest, and at the mention of the wrinkled brow and crooked jaw they had started as if each was separately touched by some specific recollection.
"'Captain Ahab,' said Tash Tego, "'that white whale must be the same that some call Moby Dick.'"
"'Moby Dick!'
shouted Ahab.
"'Do ye know the white whale, then, Tash?'
"'Does he fantail a little curious, sir, before he goes down?'
said the gay-header deliberately.
"'And has he a curious spout, too?'
said Dagu, very bushy, even for a Parmesete and mighty quick Captain Ahab.
and he have one, two, three, oh, good many iron in him hide, too, Captain," cried Quick-Weg disjointedly, all Twiskay T. B. Twisk, like him him faltering hard for a word, and screwing his hand round and round as though uncorking a bottle like him hath.
Cried Ayab.
Ay, kwee kweg!
The harpoons lie all twisted and wrenched in him.
Ay, dagoo!
His spout is a big one, like a whole shock of wheat, and white as a pile of our Nantucket wool after the great annual sheep-shearing.
Ay, tashdago!
And he fantails like a split jib in a squall.
Death and devils!
Men, it is Moby Dick!
Ye hath seen Moby Dick!
Moby Dick!
Captain Ahab," said Starbuck, who, with stub and flask, had thus far been eyeing his superior with increasing surprise, but at last seemed struck with a thought which somewhat explained all the wonder, "'Captain Ahab, I have heard of Moby Dick, but it was not Moby Dick that took off thy leg.
"'Who told thee that?'
cried Ahab, then pausing.
"'Aye, store-buck, aye, my hearties, all round, aight.
Was Moby-Dick that dismasted me bout, Moby-Dick that brought me to this dead stump I stand on now?'
"'Aye, aye,' he shouted with a terrific, loud animal sob, like that of a heart-stricken moose.
"'Aye, aye, it was that accursed white whale that raised me.
Made a poor pegging lubber of me for ever and a day, Then tossing both arms, with measureless imprecations, He shouted out, I, I!
and I'll chase him round Good-hope and round the Horn, And round the Norway maelstrom, and round Perdition's flames before I give him up, And this is what ye have shipped for, man.
To chase that white whale on both sides of land, And over all sides of earth, Till he spouts black blood and rolls Finn out.
What say ye, men?
Will ye splice hands on it now?
I think ye do look brave."
I, I," shouted the harpooneers and seamen, running closer to the excited old man.
A sharp eye for the white whale!
A sharp lance for Moby Dick!
God bless ye!
he seemed to half-sob and half-shout.
God bless ye, men!
Steward, go draw the great measure of grog.
But what's this long face about, Mr. Starbuck?
Wilt thou not chase the white whale?
Art not game for Moby Dick?
I am game for his crooked jaw.
And for the jaws of death, too, Captain Ahab, if it fairly comes in the way of the business we follow.
But I came here to hunt whales, not my commander's vengeance.
How many barrels will thy vengeance yield thee, even if thou giddest it, Captain Ahab?
It will not fetch thee much in our Nantucket market.
Nantucket Market.
Hoot, but come closer, Starbuck.
Thou requirest a little lower layer.
If money's to be the measurer, Nan, and the accountants have computed their great counting-house the globe, by girdling it with guineas, one to every three parts of an inch, then let me tell thee,
That my vengeance will fetch a great premium here."
"'Me smites his chest,' whispered Stubb.
"'What's that for?
Me thinks it rings most vast, but hollow.'"
"'Vengeance on a dumb brute!'
cried Starbuck.
"'That's simply smote thee from blindest instinct.
Madness!
To be enraged with a dumb thing, Captain Ahab, seems blasphemous.'"
Hark ye yet again, the little lower layer!
All visible objects, man, are but his pasteboard masks, bought, in each event in, the living act, the undoubted dither.
Some unknown but still reasoning thing puts forth the mouldings of its features from behind, the unreasoning mask.
If man will strike, strike through the mask,
How can the prisoner reach outside except by thrusting through the wall?
To me, the white whale is that wall shoved near to me.
Sometimes I think there's naught beyond.
But it's enough.
He tasks me, he heaps me.
I see in him outrageous strength.
With an inscrutable malice sinew in it.
That inscrutable thing is chiefly what I hate.
And be the white whale agent, or be the white whale principal.
I will wreak that hate upon him.
Talk not to me of blasphemy, man.
I'd stripe the sun if it insulted me.
For could the sun do that, then could I do the other other sins.
There is ever a sort of fair play herein, Jealousy presiding over all creations.
But not my master, man, is even that fair play.
Who's over me?
Truth hath no confines.
Take off thine eye.
More intolerable than fiend's glarings is adultish stare.
So, so, so redness and palest my heat Has melted thee to anger glow.
But look ye, Starbuck, What is said in heat, the thing unsays itself.
There are men from whom warm words are small in dignity.
I meant not to incense thee.
Let it go.
Look, see under Turkish cheeks, Of spotted torn living, breathing pictures, Painted by the sun, the pagan leopards, The unwrecking and unworshipping things That live and seek and give no reasons For the torrid life they feel.
The crew, man, the crew!
Are they not one and all with Ahab In this matter of the whale?
See, stub!
He laughs.
Sea yonder, Julian," he snorts to think of it.
Stand up amid the general hurricane.
Thy one-tossed dappling cannot.
Starbuck.
And what is it?
Reckon it.
Tis but to help strike a fin.
No wondrous feat for Starbuck.
What is it more from this?
One poor hunt, then.
The best lance out of all Nantucket.
Surely he will not hang back When every foremast hand Has clutched a whetstone.
Ah, constrainings, seize these, oop!
Say, the billow lifts thee.
Speak, but speak.
Ay, ay, thy silence, then.
That voice is thee aside.
Something shot from my dilated nostrils, He has inhaled it in his lungs.
Starbuck now is mine, Cannot oppose me now without rebellion.
God, keep me, keep us all.
murmured Starbuck lowly.
But in his joy at the enchanted, tacit acquiescence of the mate, Ahab did not hear his foreboding indication, nor yet the low laugh from the hold, nor yet the presaging vibrations of the winds and the cordage, nor is the hollow flap of the sails against the masts, as for a moment their hearts sank in.
For again Starbuck's downcast eyes lighted up with the stubbornness of life.
The subterranean laugh died away, the winds blew on the sails filled out, the ship heaved and rolled as before.
Ah, ye admonitions and warnings, why stay ye not when ye come?
But rather are ye predictions than warnings, ye shadows, yet not so much predictions from without as verifications of the full.
The measure!
cried Ahab.
Receiving the brimming pewter and turning to the harponeers, he ordered them to produce their weapons, then ranging them before him near the capstan, with their harpoons in their hands, while his three mates stood at his side with their lances, and the rest of the ship's company formed a circle round the group.
He took for an instant searchingly eyeing every man of his crew.
But those wild eyes met his, as the blood-shot eyes of the prairie wolves meet the eye of their leader ere he rushes on at their head in the trail of the bison, but alas, only to fall into the hidden snare of the Indian.
Drink and pass, he cried, handing the heavy-charged flagon to the nearest seaman.
The crew alone now drink, round with it, round.
Short draughts, long swallows, man, tis hot as Satan's hoof.
So, so Sir Tenning's round excellently.
It spiralizes in ye, forks out at the serpent's snappet eye.
Well done, almost drained.
That way it wind, this way it comes, and it meteors a hollow.
Men, ye seem the years, So brooming life is gulped and gone, Steward, refill.
Attend now, my braves, I have mustard ye all round this capstan, And ye mates, flake me with your lances, And ye harpooneers, stand there with your irons, And ye stout mariners, ring me in, That I may in some sort revive a noble custom Of my fishermen fathers before me.
Oh, men, you will yet see that—boy, come back!
Bad pennies come not sooner.
Hand it me.
Why, now this pewter had run brimming again.
Wert not thou St.
Vitus in beway thou ague?
Advance, ye mates.
Cross your lances full before me.
Well done.
Let me touch the axis.
So saying, with extended arm, he grasped the three level, radiating lances at their crossed centre, while so doing, suddenly and nervously twitched them, and while, glancing intently from starbook to stub, from stub to flask, it seemed as though by some nameless interior volition
He would fain have shocked into them the same fiery emotion accumulated within the laden jar of his own magnetic life.
The three mates quailed before his strong, sustained, and mystic aspect.
Stub and flask looked sideways from him, the honest eye of Starbuck fell downright.
"'In vain!'
cried Ahab, but maybe tis well.
For did ye three but once take the full force shock, then my known electric thing, that had perhaps expired from out me, perchance too it would have dropped ye dead.'
Perchance ye need it not.
Down, lances, and now, ye mates, I do appoint ye three cup-bearers, To my three pagan kinsmen thereyon, Three most honourable gentlemen and noblemen, My valiant harpooneers.
Disdain the task— What, when the great Pope washes the feet of beggars Using his tiara for ewer?
Oh, my sweet cardinals!
Your own condescension!
That shall bend you to it.
I do not order ye to you, will it?
Cut your ceasings and draw the poles, you harpooneers.
Silently obeying the order, the three harpooneers now stood with the detached iron part of their harpoons, some three feet long, held, barged up before him.
Stab me not with that keen steel.
Cant them over.
Know ye not the goblet end?
Turn up the socket.
So, so now, ye cun-bearers, advance.
The irons, take them, hold them, while I fill."
Forthwith, slowly going from one officer to the other, he brimmed the harpoon-sockets with the fiery waters from the pewter.
Now, three to three, ye stand.
Commend the murderous chalices.
Bestow them, ye who are now made parties to this indissoluble league.
Ah, Starbuck, but the deed is done.
Yon ratifying sun now waits to sit upon it.
Drink, ye harpooniers, drink and swear, Ye men that mend the deathful whale-boats bow death to Moby Dick.
God hunt us all, if we do not hunt Moby Dick to his death.
The long barbed steel goblets were lifted, and to cries and maledictions against the white whale, the spirits were simultaneously quaffed down with a hiss.
Starbuck paled, and turned, and shivered.
Once more, and finally, the replenished pewter went the rounds among the frantic crew.
When, waving his free hand to them, they all dispersed, and Ahab retired within his cabin.