Chapter 64 - Stubbs' Supper. Stubbs' whale had been killed some distance from the ship.
It was a calm, so, forming a tandem of three boats, we commenced the slow business of towing the trophy to the Pequod.
And now, as we eighteen men with our thirty-six arms and one hundred and eighty thumbs and fingers, slowly toiled hour after hour upon that inert, sluggish corpse in the sea,
And it seemed hardly to budge at all, except at long intervals.
Good evidence was hereby furnished of the enormousness of the mass we moved.
For, upon the great canal of Hanghou, or whatever they call it, in China, four or five laborers on the footpath will draw a bulky freighted junk at the rate of a mile an hour.
But this grand argosy we towed heavily forged along, as if laden with pig lead in bulk.
Darkness came on, but three lights up and down in the Pequod's main rigging dimly guided our way, till drawing nearer we saw Ahab dropping one of several more lanterns over the bulwarks.
Vacantly eyeing the heaving whale for a moment, he issued the usual orders for securing it for the night, and then handing his lantern to a seaman, went his way into the cabin and did not come forward again until morning.
Though, in overseeing the pursuit of this whale, Captain Ahab had evinced his customary activity to call it so, yet now that the creature was dead, some vague dissatisfaction or impatience or despair seemed working in him, as if the sight of that dead body reminded him that Moby Dick was yet to be slain.
And though a thousand other whales were brought to his ship, all that would not one jot advance his grand monomaniac object.
Very soon you would have thought from the sound on the Pequod's decks that all hands were preparing to cast anchor in the deep, for heavy chains are being dragged along the deck and thrust rattling out of the portholes.
but by those clanking links the vast corpse itself, not the ship, is to be moored.
Tied by the head to the stern and by the tail to the bows, the whale now lies with its black hull close to the vessels, and seen through the darkness of the night, which obscured the spars and rigging aloft.
The two ship and whale seem yoked together like colossal bullocks, whereof one reclines while the other remains standing.
The strongest and most reliable hold which the ship has upon the whale when moored alongside is by the flukes or tail, and as from its greater density that part is relatively heavier than any other excepting the side fins, its flexibility even in death causes it to sink low beneath the surface, so that with the hand you cannot get at it from the boat in order to put the chain round it.
But this difficulty is ingeniously overcome.
A small, strong line is prepared with a wooden float at its outer end, and a weight in its middle, while the other end is secured to the ship.
By adroit management the wooden float is made to rise on the other side of the mass, so that now having girdled the whale, the chain is readily made to follow suit, and being slipped along the body, is at last locked fast round the smallest part of the tail, at the point of junction with its broad flukes or lobes.
If Moody Ahab was now all quiescence, at least so far as could be known on deck, Stub, his second mate, flushed with conquest, betrayed in unusual but still good-natured excitement.
Such an unwanted bustle was he in that, the staid Starbuck, his official superior, quietly resigned to him for the time the sole management of affairs.
One small, helping cause of all this liveliness in Stubb was soon made strangely manifest.
Stubb was a high liver.
He was somewhat intemperately fond of the whale as a flavorish thing to his palate.
A steak, a steak, ere I sleep.
You, Dagoo, overboard you go, and cut me one from his small.
Here be it known, that though these wild fishermen do not, as a general thing, and according to the great military maxim, make the enemy defray the current expenses of the war, at least before realizing the proceeds of the voyage, yet now and then you find some of these Nantucketers who have a genuine relish for that particular part of the sperm whale designated by stub, comprising the tapering extremity of the body.
About midnight that steak was cut and cooked and lighted by two lanterns of sperm oil.
Stubb stoutly stood up to his spermaceti supper at the capstan head, as if that capstan were a sideboard.
Nor was Stubb the only banqueter on whale's flesh that night.
Mingling their mumblings with his own mastications, thousands on thousands of sharks, swarming round the dead leviathan, smackingly feasted on its fatness.
The few sleepers below in their bunks were often startled by the sharp slapping of their tails against the hull within a few inches of the sleepers' hearts.
Peering over the side you could just see them as before you heard them, wallowing in the sullen black waters and turning over on their backs as they scooped out huge globular pieces of the whale of the bigness of a human head.
This particular feat of the shark seems all but miraculous.
How at such an apparently unassailable surface they contrive to gouge out such symmetrical mouthfuls remains a part of the universal problem of all things.
The mark they thus leave on the whale may best be likened to the hollow made by a carpenter in countersinking for a screw.
Though amid all the smoking horror and scythe-stacks, like stack-slash-shove, like hungry dogs round a tassel where their red meat is being carved, ready to bolt down every killed man that is tossed to them.
And though, while the valiant butchers over the deck-table are thus cannibly carving each other's live meat with carving-knives all gilded and tasseled, the sharks also, with their jewel-hilted mouths, are quarrelsomely carving away under the table at the dead meat.
And though, were you to turn the whole affair upside down, it would still be pretty much the same thing.
That is to say, a shocking sharkish business enough for all parties.
And those sharks also are the invariable outriders of all slave ships crossing the Atlantic, systematically trotting.
If you have never seen that sight, then suspend your decision about the propriety of devil worship and the expediency of conciliating the devil.
But, as yet, Stubb heeded not the mumblings of the banquet that was going on so nigh him.
No more than the sharks heeded the smacking of his own epicurean lips.
Cook!
Where's that old fleece?
He cried at length, widening his legs still further, as if to form a more secure base for his supper, and, at the same time, darting his fork into the dish, as if stabbing with his lance.
Cook, you cook!
Sail this way, cook!
The old black, not in any very high glee at having been previously roused from his warm hammock at a most unseasonable hour, came shambling along from his galley, for, like many old blacks, there was something the matter with his knee-pans, which he did not keep.
Well scoured like his other pans, this old fleece, as they called him, came shuffling and limping along, assisting his step with his tongs, which, after a clumsy fashion, were made of straightened iron hoops.
This old ebony floundered along, and, in obedience to the word of command, came to a dead stop on the opposite side of Stubb's sideboard, when, with both hands folded before him and resting on his two-legged cane, he bent.
Cook, said Stubb, rapidly lifting a rather reddish morsel to his mouth.
Don't you think this steak is rather overdone?
You've been beating this steak too much, cook.
It's too tender.
Don't I always say that to be good?
A whale steak must be tough.
There are those sharks now over the side.
Don't you see they prefer it tough and rare?
What a shindy they are kicking up.
Cook, go and talk to them.
Tell them they are welcome to help themselves civilly and in moderation, but they must keep quiet.
Blast me, if I can hear my own voice.
Away, cook, and deliver my message.
Here, take this lantern, snatching one from his sideboard.
Now then, go and preach to him.
Sullenly taking the offered lantern, Old Fleece limped across the deck to the bulwarks, and then, with one hand dropping his light low over the sea,
so as to get a good view of his congregation.
With the other hand, he solemnly flourished his tongs, and leaning far over the side in a mumbling voice, began addressing the sharks, while Stub, softly crawling behind, overheard all that was said.
Fellow Critters, I'se ordered here to say dat you must stop dat damn noise dere.
You hear?
Stop dat damn smackin' of da lips.
Massa Stubs say dat you can fill you damn bellies up to da hatchings, but by gore, you must stop dat damn racket.
Cook, hear interposed Stubb accompanying the word with a sudden slap on the shoulder.
Cook, why, damn your eyes, you mustn't swear that way when you're preaching.
That's no way to convert sinners, Cook.
Who dat?
Den preach to him yourself, sullenly turning to go.
No, Cook, go on, go on.
Well, Den, belubed fellow critters, write, exclaimed Stubb approvingly.
Coax him to it, try that, and Fleece continued.
Do you, is all sharks, and by nature, wary, voracious, Yet I say to you, fellow critters, dat dat voraciousness, Top dat dam slappin' ob da tail, How you tink to here, suppose you keep up Such a dam slappin' and bitin' dare.
Cook, cried Stub, collaring him, I won't have that swearing, Talk to him gentlemanly.
Once more the sermon proceeded, Your voraciousness, fellow critters, I don't blame you so much for, Dot is notter and can't be helped, But to gobern dot wicked notter, Dot is de pint.
You is sharks, Sarton, But if you gobern de shark in you, Why den you be angel?
For all angel is notting more, Dan de shark well goberned.
Now look here, brethren, just try once to be seeble, a-helping yourselves from dat whale.
Don't be tearin' to blubber out your neighbor's mout, I say.
Is not one shark dude right as toter to dat whale?
And, by gore, none on you has de right to dat whale.
Dat whale belong to someone else.
I know some o' you has Barry Brigg mout, Brigger Dan odors.
But den de brig mout sometimes has de small bellies.
So, dat de brigness of de mout is not to swaller wid, but to bid off de blubber for de small fry of sharks dat can't get into de scrooge to help demselves."
Well done, old fleece," cried Stubb.
That's Christianity.
Go on.
No use goin' on, the damn willins will keep a-scougin' and slappin' each odor, Massa Stubb.
They don't hear one word.
No use a-preachin' to such damn guttons as you call them, till their bellies is full and their bellies is bottomless.
And when they do get them full, they won't hear you then, For then they sink in the sea, go fast to sleep on the coral, And can't hear noting at all, no more, for ever and eber.
Upon my soul I am about of the same opinion, So give the benediction, fleece, and I'll away to my supper.
Upon this, Fleece, holding both hands over the fishy mob, raised his shrill voice and cried, Cust, fellow critters, kick up to damnedest row as ever you can, fill you damn bellies till they bust and den die.
Now cook, said Stub, resuming his supper at the capstan.
Stand just where you stood before, there, over against me, and pay particular attention.
All dention, said Fleece, again stooping over upon his tongs in the desired position.
"'Well,' said Stubb, helping himself freely meanwhile, "'I shall now go back to the subject of the steak.
"'In the first place, how old are you, cook?'
"'What dat do with da talk?'
said the old black testily.
"'Silence!
How old are you, cook?'
"'Bout ninety, they say,' he gloomily muttered.
"'And you have lived in this world hard upon one hundred years, cook, "'and don't know yet how to cook a whale steak?'
Rapidly bolting another mouthful at the last word, "'so that morsel seemed a continuation of the question.
Where were you born, Cook?
Hindah Hatchway, in ferryboat.
Going over to Roanoke.
Born in a ferryboat?
That's queer, too.
But I want to know what country you were born in, Cook.
Didn't I say to Roanoke country?
He cried sharply.
No, you didn't, Cook.
But I'll tell you what I'm coming to, Cook.
You must go home and be born over again.
You don't know how to cook a whale steak yet.
Breast my soul, if I cook noter one," he growled angrily, turning round to depart.
Come back here, cook.
Here, hand me those tongs.
Now take that bit of steak there, and tell me if you think that steak cooked as it should be.
Take it, I say.
Holding the tongs towards him, take it and taste it.
Faintly smacking his withered lips over it for a moment, the old negro muttered, best-cooked hick-eye eber taste, juicy, berry juicy.
Juicy, berry juicy.
"'Cook,' said Stubb, squaring himself once more.
"'Do you belong to the church?'
"'Passed one once in Cape Town,' said the old man sullenly.
"'And you have once in your life passed a holy church in Cape Town, where you doubtless overheard a holy parson addressing his hearers as his beloved fellow-creatures, have you, Cook?
And yet you come here and tell me such a dreadful lie as you did just now, eh?'
said Stubb.
"'Where do you expect to go to, Cook?'
Go to bed very soon," he mumbled, half-turning as he spoke.
Avast!
Heave to!
I mean, when you die, Cook, it's an awful question.
Now what's your answer?
When this old brack man dies, said the negro slowly, changing his whole air and demeanor, he hisself won't go nowhere, but some breast angel will come and fetch him.
Fetch him?
How?
In a coach and four as they fetched Elijah.
And fetch him where?
"'Up, dear,' said Fleece, holding his tongs straight over his head, and keeping it there very solemnly.
"'So, then, you expect to go up into our main top, do you, Cook, when you are dead?
But don't you know the higher you climb, the colder it gets?
Main top, eh?'
"'Didn't say datal,' said Fleece, again in the sulks.
"'You said up there, didn't you?
And now look yourself, and see where your tongs are pointing.'
But, perhaps you expect to get into heaven by crawling through the lover's hole, cook.
But, no, no, cook, you don't get there, except you go the regular way, round by the rigging.
It's a ticklish business, but must be done, or else it's no go.
But none of us are in heaven yet.
Drop your tongs, cook, and hear my orders.
Do you hear?
Hold your hat in one hand and clap tether atop of your heart when I'm giving my orders, cook.
What, that your heart, there?
That's your gizzard, aloft, aloft, that's it, now you have it.
Hold it there now and pay attention.
"'All dention,' said the old black, with both hands placed as desired, vainly wriggling his grizzled head, as if to get both ears in front at one and the same time.
"'Well, then, cook.
You see this whale-steak of yours was so very bad that I have put it out of sight as soon as possible.
You see that, don't you?
Well, for the future, when you cook another whale-steak for my private table here, the Capstan, I'll tell you what to do so as not to spoil it by overdoing.'
Hold the steak in one hand and show a live coal to it with the other.
That done.
Dish it, die here.
And now tomorrow, cook.
When we are cutting in the fish, be sure you stand by to get the tips of his fins, have them put in pickle.
As for the ends of the flukes, have them soused, cook.
There, now ye may go.
But Fleece had hardly got three paces off when he was recalled.
Cook, give me cutlets for supper tomorrow night in the mid-watch.
D'you hear?
Away you sail then.
Haloa, stop, make a bow before you go.
Avast, heaving again.
Whale balls for breakfast, don't forget.
Wish by gore, whale eat him, stead of him eat whale.
I'm breast if he ain't more of Sharkdan Massashark hisself, muttered the old man, limping away, with which sage ejaculation he went to his hammock.