Chapter 81 - The Pequod Meets the Virgin
Chapter 81 - The Pequod Meets the Virgin. The predestinated day arrived, and we duly met the ship, Jungfrau, Derek de Deer, Master of Bremen.
At one time the greatest whaling people in the world, the Dutch and Germans are now among the least, but here and there at very wide intervals of latitude and longitude, you still occasionally meet with their flag in the Pacific.
For some reason, the Zhongfrau seemed quite eager to pay her respects.
While yet some distance from the Pequod, she rounded to, and dropping a boat, her captain was impelled towards us, impatiently standing in the bows instead of the stern.
What has he in his hand there?"
cried Starbuck, pointing to something wavingly held by the German.
Impossible!
A lamp-feeder!
Not that, said Stubb.
No, no, it's a coffee-pot, Mr. Starbuck.
He's coming off to make us our coffee, is the Yarman.
Don't you see that big tin can there alongside of him?
That's his boiling water.
Oh, he's all right, is the Yarman.
"'Go along with you,' cried Flask.
"'It's a lamp-feeder and an oil can.
"'He's out of oil and has come a-begging.'"
However curious it may seem for an oil ship to be borrowing oil on the whale ground, and however much it may invertedly contradict the old proverb about carrying coals to Newcastle, yet sometimes such a thing really happens.
And in the present case, Captain Derek DeDeer did indubitably conduct a lamp-feeder, as Flask did declare.
As he mounted the deck, Ahab abruptly accosted him, without at all heeding what he had in his hand.
But in his broken lingo, the German soon evinced his complete ignorance of the white whale, immediately turning the conversation to his lamp-feeder and oil can, with some remarks touching as having to turn into his hammock at night in profound darkness.
his last drop of Bremen oil being gone, and not a single flying fish yet captured to supply the deficiency, concluding by hinting that his ship was indeed what in the fishery is technically called a clean one, that is, an empty one, well deserving the name of Jumfrau or the Virgin.
His necessities supplied, Derek departed, but he had not gained his ship's side, when whales were almost simultaneously raised from the mast-heads of both vessels, and so eager for the chase was Derek, that without pausing to put his oil can and lamp-feeder aboard, he slewed round his boat and made after the leviathan lamp-feeders.
Now, the game having risen to leeward, he and the other three German boats that soon followed him, had considerably the start of the Pequod's keels.
There were eight whales, an average pod.
Aware of their danger, they were going all abreast with great speed straight before the wind, rubbing their flanks as closely as so many spans of horses in harness.
they left a great wide wake, as though continually unrolling a great wide parchment upon the sea.
Full in this rabid wake, and many fathoms in the rear, swam a huge, humped old bull, which by his comparatively slow progress, as well as by the unusual yellowish incrustations overgrowing him, seemed afflicted with the jaundice or some other infirmity.
Whether this whale belonged to the pod in advance seemed questionable, for it is not customary for such venerable leviathans to be at all social.
Nevertheless he stuck to their wake, though indeed their backwater must have retarded him, because the white bone or swell at his broad muzzle was a dashed one, like the swell formed when two hostile currents meet.
His spout was short, slow and laborious, coming forth with a choking sort of gush and spending itself in torn shreds, followed by strange subterranean commotions in him, which seemed to have egress at his other buried extremity causing the waters behind him to up-bubble.
Who's got some paragoric?"
said Stubb.
He has the stomachache, I'm afraid.
Lord, think of having half an acre of stomachache.
Adverse winds are holding mad Christmas in him, boys.
It's the first foul wind I ever knew to blow from a stern.
But look, did ever wail yaw so before?
It must be he's lost his tiller.
As an overladen Indiaman bearing down the Hindostan coast with a deckload of frightened horses, careens, berries, rolls, and wallows on her way, so did this old whale heave his aged bulk, and now and then, partly turning over on his cumbrous rib-ends, expose the cause of his devious wake in the unnatural stump of his starboard fin.
Whether he had lost that fin in battle or had been born without it, it were hard to say.
Only wait a bit, old chap, and I'll give you a sling for that wounded arm, cried cruel Flask, pointing to the whale-line near him.
Mind he don't sling thee with it, cried Starbuck.
Give way, or the German will have him.
With one intent, all the combined rival boats were pointed for this one fish, because not only was he the largest and therefore the most valuable whale, but he was nearest to them, and the other whales were going with such great velocity, moreover, as almost to defy pursuit for the time.
At this juncture, the Pequod's keels had shot by the three German boats last lowered, but from the great start he had had, Derek's boat still led the chase, though every moment neared by his foreign rivals.
The only thing they feared was that from being already so nigh to his mark, he would be enabled to dart his iron before they could completely overtake and pass him.
As for Derek, he seemed quite confident that this would be the case, and occasionally with a deriding gesture shook his lamp feeder at the other boats.
The ungracious and ungrateful dog, cried Starbuck.
He mocks and dares me with the very poor box I filled for him not five minutes ago.
Then in his old intense whisper, Give way, greyhounds!
Dog to it!
I tell you what it is, men, cried Stubb to his crew.
It's against my religion to get mad, But I'd like to eat that villainous Yarman.
Pull, won't ye?
Are ye going to let that rascal beat ye?
Do ye love brandy?
A hog's head of brandy, then, to the best man.
Come, why don't some of ye burst a blood vessel?
Who's that been dropping an anchor overboard?
We don't budge an inch, we're becalmed.
Halloo, here's grass growing in the boat's bottom, And by the Lord, the mast there's budding.
This won't do, boys.
Look at that yarman.
The short and long of it is, men.
Will ye spit fire or not?
Oh, see the suds he makes," cried Flask, dancing up and down.
What a hump!
Oh, Dio, pile on the beef, lays like a log.
Oh, my lads, do o' spring slapjacks and quahogs for supper, you know, my lads.
Baked clams and muffins O-D-O-D Spring He's a hundred-barreler Don't lose him now Don't, oh, don't See that yarman Oh, won't ye pull for your duff, my lads Such a sog, such a sogger Don't ye love sperm There goes three thousand dollars, men A bank, a whole bank The Bank of England O-D-O-D-O-D-O-D-O-D-O-D-O-G
At this moment Derek was in the act of pitching his lamp feeder at the advancing boats, and also his oil can, perhaps with the double view of retarding his rival's way, and at the same time economically accelerating his own by the momentary impetus of the backward toss.
The unmannerly Dutch dogger!
cried Stub.
Pull now, men, like fifty thousand line-of-battleship loads of red-haired devils.
What you say, Tashtego, are you the man to snap your spine in two-and-twenty pieces for the honor of old gayhead?
What you say, I say, pull like God damn!"
cried the Indian.
Fiercely but evenly incited by the taunts of the German, the Pequod's three boats now began ranging almost abreast and, so disposed, momentarily neared him.
in that fine, loose, chivalrous attitude of the headsman when drawing near to his prey.
The three mates stood up proudly, occasionally backing the after oarsman with an exhilarating cry of, There she slides!
Now!
Hurrah for the White Ash Breeze!
Down with the Yarmen!
Sail over him!
But so decided, an original start had Derek had.
That spite of all their gallantry, he would have proved the victor in this race, had not a righteous judgment descended upon him in a crab which caught the blade of his midship oarsman.
while this clumsy lubber was striving to free his white ash, and while, in consequence, Derek's boat was nigh to capsizing, and he thundering away at his men in a mighty rage, that was a good time for Starbuck, Stub, and Flask.
With a shout, they took a mortal start forwards, and slantingly ranged up on the German's quarter.
An instant more, and all four boats were diagonally in the whale's immediate wake, while stretching from them, on both sides, was the foaming swell that he made.
It was a terrific, most pitiable and maddening sight.
The whale was now going head out and sending his spout before him in a continual tormented jet, while his one poor fin beat his side in an agony of fright.
Now to this hand, now to that, he yawed in his faltering flight, and still at every billow that he broke, he spasmodically sank in the sea or sideways rolled towards the sky his one beating fin.
So have I seen a bird with clipped wing making affrighted broken circles in the air, vainly striving to escape the piratical hawks?
But the bird has a voice, and with plaintive cries will make known her fear.
But the fear of this vast, dumb brood of the sea was chained up and enchanted in him.
He had no voice save that choking respiration through his spiracle, and this made the sight of him unspeakably pitiable, while still, in his amazing bulk, portcullis jaw, and omnipotent tail, there was enough to apple the stoutest man who so pitied.
Seeing now that but a very few moments more would give the Pequod's boats the advantage, and rather than be thus foiled of his game, Derret chose to hazard what to him must have seemed a most unusually long dart, ere the last chance would for ever escape.
But no sooner did his harpooneer stand up for the stroke than all three tigers—Kwekweg, Tashtego, Dagu—instinctively sprang to their feet, and standing in a diagonal row, simultaneously pointed their barbs and darted over the head of the German harpooneer.
Their three Nantucket irons entered the whale, blinding vapors of foam and white fire.
The three boats, in the first fury of the whale's headlong rush, bumped the Germans aside with such force that both Derek and his baffled harpooner were spilled out and sailed over by the three flying keels.
Don't be afraid, my butterboxes, cried Stubb, casting a passing glance upon them as he shot by.
You'll be picked up presently, all right?
I saw some sharks astern.
St.
Bernard's dogs, you know, relieve distressed travelers.
Hurrah!
This is the way to sail now.
Every keel a sunbeam.
Hurrah!
Here we go like three tin kettles at the tail of a mad cougar.
This puts me in mind of fastening to an elephant in a tillberry on a plain.
Makes the wheelspokes fly, boys, when you fasten to him that way.
And there's danger of being pitched out, too, when you strike a hill.
Hurrah!
This is the way a fellow feels when he's going to Davy Jones.
All a rush down an endless inclined plain.
Hurrah!
This whale carries the everlasting mail.
But the monster's run was a brief one.
giving a sudden gasp he tumultuously sounded.
With a grating rush the three lines flew round the lauderheads with such a force as to gouge deep grooves in them.
While so fearful were the harpooneers that this rapid sounding would soon exhaust the lines.
That using all their dexterous might, they caught repeated smoking turns with the rope to hold on till at last.
Owing to the perpendicular strain from the lead-lined chocks of the boats, whence the three ropes went straight down into the blue.
The gunwales of the bows were almost even with the water, while the three sterns tilted high in the air.
and the whale soon ceasing to sound.
For some time they remained in that attitude, fearful of expending more line, though the position was a little ticklish.
But though boats have been taken down and lost in this way, yet it is this, holding on, as it is called, this hooking up by the sharp barbs of his live flesh from the back, this it is that often torments the Leviathan into soon rising again to meet the sharp lance of his foes.
Yet not to speak of the peril of the thing, it is to be doubted whether this course is always the best, for it is but reasonable to presume that the longer the stricken whale stays underwater, the more he is exhausted.
Because, owing to the enormous surface of him, in a full-grown sperm whale, something less than two thousand square feet,
The pressure of the water is immense.
We all know what an astonishing atmospheric weight we ourselves stand up under, even here, above ground, in the air.
How vast, then, the burden of a whale, bearing on his back a column of two hundred fathoms of ocean.
It must at least equal the weight of fifty atmospheres.
One whaleman has estimated it at the weight of twenty line of battleships with all their guns and stores and men on board.
As the three boats lay there on that gently rolling sea, gazing down into its eternal blue noon, and as not a single groan or cry of any sort, nay, not so much as a ripple or a bubble came up from its depths,
What landsman would have thought, that beneath all that silence and placidity, the utmost monster of the seas was writhing and wrenching in agony?
Not eight inches of perpendicular rope were visible at the bows.
Seems it credible that by three such thin threads the great Leviathan was suspended like the big weight to an eight-day clock.
Suspended, and to what?
To three bits of board,
Is this the creature of whom it was once so triumphantly said, Canst thou fill his skin with barbed irons, Or his head with fish-spears?
The sword of him that layeth at him cannot hold, The spear, the dart, nor the habergone, He esteemeth iron as straw, The arrow cannot make him flee, Darts are counted as stubble, He loggeth at the shaking of a spear.
This, the creature?
This, he?
Oh, that unfulfillments should follow the prophets!
For with the strength of a thousand thighs in his tail, Leviathan had run his head under the mountains of the sea to hide him from the Pequod's fish-spears.
In that sloping afternoon sunlight, the shadows that the three boats sent down beneath the surface must have been long enough and broad enough to shade half Xerxes's army.
Who can tell how appalling to the wounded whale must have been such huge phantoms flitting over his head?
"'Stand by, men,' he stirs," cried Starbuck, as the three lines suddenly vibrated in the water, distinctly conducting upwards to them, as by magnetic wires the life-and-death throbs of the whale, so that every oarsman felt them in his seat.
The next moment, relieved in great part from the downward strain at the bows, the boats gave a sudden bounce upwards, as a small ice-field will, when a dense herd of white bears are scared from it into the sea.
"'Haul in!
Haul in!'
cried Starbuck again.
"'He's rising!'
The lines—of which, hardly an instant before, not one hand's breath could have been gained—were now in long, quick coils flung back all dripping into the boats, and soon the whale broke water within two ships' lengths of the hunters.
His motions plainly denoted his extreme exhaustion.
In most land animals, there are certain valves or floodgates in many of their veins, whereby when wounded, the blood is in some degree at least instantly shut off in certain directions.
Not so with the whale, one of whose peculiarities it is to have an entire non-valvular structure of the blood vessels, so that when pierced even by so small a point as a harpoon, a deadly drain is at once begun upon his whole arterial system.
And when this is heightened by the extraordinary pressure of water at a great distance below the surface, his life may be said to pour from him in incessant streams.
Yet so vast is the quantity of blood in him, and so distant and numerous its interior fountains, that he will keep thus bleeding and bleeding for a considerable period, even as in a drought a river will flow, whose source is in the well-springs of far-off and undiscernable hills.
Even now, when the boats pulled upon this whale, and perilously drew over his swaying flukes, and the lances were darted into him, they were followed by steady jets from the new-made wound, which kept continually playing while the natural spout hole in his head was only at intervals, however rapid, sending its affrighted moisture into the air.
From this last vent no blood yet came, because no vital part of him had thus far been struck.
His life, as they significantly call it, was untouched.
As the boats now more closely surrounded him, the whole upper part of his form, with much of it that is ordinarily submerged, was plainly revealed.
His eyes, or rather, the places where his eyes had been, were beheld.
as strange misgrown masses gather in the knot holes of the noblest oaks when prostrate.
So from the points which the whale's eyes had once occupied now protruded blind bulbs horribly pitiable to see.
but pity there was none.
For all his old age, and his one arm, and his blind eyes, he must die the death and be murdered, in order to light the gay bridles and other merry-makings of men, and also to illuminate the solemn churches that preach unconditional inoffensiveness by all to all.
Still rolling in his blood, at last he partially disclosed a strangely discolored bunch or protuberance the size of a bushel low down on the flank.
A nice spot, cried Flask.
Just let me prick him there once.
A vast, cried Starbuck.
There's no need of that.
But humane Starbuck was too late.
At the instant of the dart, an ulcerous jet shot from this cruel wound, and goaded by it into more than sufferable anguish, the whale now spouting thick blood, with swift fury blindly darted at the craft, bespattering them and their glorying crews all over with showers of gore, capsizing Flask's boat and marring the bows.
It was his deathstroke.
For, by this time, so spent was he by loss of blood, that he helplessly rolled away from the wreck he had made, lay panting on his side, impotently flapped with his stumped fin, then over and over slowly revolved like a waning world, turned up the white secrets of his belly, lay like a log, and died.
It was most piteous, that last expiring spout.
as when by unseen hands the water is gradually drawn off from some mighty fountain, and with half-stifled melancholy gurglings the spray column lowers and lowers to the ground.
So the last long dying spout of the whale.
Soon, while the crews were awaiting the arrival of the ship, the body showed symptoms of sinking with all its treasures unrifled.
Immediately, by Starbucks orders, lines were secured to it at different points, so that air-long every boat was a buoy, the sunken whale being suspended a few inches beneath them by the cords.
By very heedful management, when the ship drew nigh, the whale was transferred to her side and was strongly secured there by the stiffest flupe-chains, for it was plain that unless artificially upheld, the body would at once sink to the bottom.
it so chanced that almost upon first cutting into him with the spade, the entire length of a corroded harpoon was found embedded in his flesh, on the lower part of the bunch before described.
But as the stumps of harpoons are frequently found in the dead bodies of captured whales, with the flesh perfectly healed around them, and no prominence of any kind to denote their place, therefore there must needs have been some other unknown reason in the present case fully to account for the ulceration alluded to.
But still more curious was the fact of a lancehead of stone being found in him, not far from the buried iron, the flesh perfectly firm about it.
Who had darted that stone lance, and when?
It might have been darted by some Norse West Indian long before America was discovered.
What other marvels might have been rummaged out of this monstrous cabinet there is no telling.
but a sudden stop was put to further discoveries, by the ships being unprecedentedly dragged over sideways to the sea, owing to the body's immensely increasing tendency to sink.
However, Starbuck, who had the ordering of affairs, hung on to it to the last, hung on to it so resolutely, indeed, that when at length the ship would have been capsized, if still persisting in locking arms with the body.
Then, when the command was given to break clear from it, such was the immovable strain upon the timber heads to which the flute chains and cables were fastened that it was impossible to cast them off.
Meantime, everything in the Pequod was a slant.
To cross to the other side of the deck was like walking up the steep, gabled roof of a house.
The ship groaned and gassed.
Many of the ivory inlayings of her bulwarks and cabins were started from their places, by the unnatural dislocation.
In vain, hand spikes and crows were brought to bear upon the immovable fluke chains, to pry them adrift from the timber heads, and so low had the whale now settled that the submerged ends could not be at all approached.
while every moment whole tons of ponderosity seemed added to the sinking bulk and the ship seemed on the point of going over.
Hold on, hold on, won't ye?"
cried Stubb to the body.
Don't be in such a devil of a hurry to sink.
By thunder, men, we must do something or go for it.
No use prying there.
Avast, I say, with your hand-spikes, and run one of ye for a prayer-book and a pen-knife, and cut the big chains.
Aye, aye, cried Queequeg, and seizing the carpenter's heavy hatchet, he leaned out of a porthole, and steel to iron, began slashing at the largest floop-chains.
but a few strokes full of sparks were given when the exceeding strain affected the rest.
With a terrific snap, every fastening went adrift, the ship righted, the carcass sank.
Now, this occasional inevitable sinking of the recently killed sperm whale is a very curious thing, nor has any fisherman yet adequately accounted for it.
Usually the dead sperm whale floats with great buoyancy, with its side or belly considerably elevated above the surface.
If the only whales that thus sank were old, meager, and broken-hearted creatures, their pads of lard diminished and all their bones heavy and rheumatic, then you might with some reason assert that this sinking is caused by an uncommon specific gravity in the fish.
So sinking, consequent upon this absence of buoyant matter in him,
But it is not so.
For young whales, in the highest health and swelling with noble aspirations, prematurely cut off in the warm flush and may of life, with all their panting lard about them, even these brawny, buoyant heroes do sometimes sink.
Be it said, however, that the sperm whale is far less liable to this accident than any other species.
Where one of that sort go down, twenty right whales do.
This difference in the species is no doubt imputable, in no small degree to the greater quantity of bone in the right whale, his venetian blinds alone sometimes weighing more than a ton.
From this encumbrance the sperm whale is wholly free.
But there are instances where, after the lapse of many hours or several days, the sunken whale again rises, more buoyant than in life.
But the reason of this is obvious.
Gases are generated in him.
He swells to a prodigious magnitude, becomes a sort of animal balloon.
A line of battleship could hardly keep him under then.
In the shore whaling, on soundings among the bays of New Zealand, when a right whale gives token of sinking, they fasten buoys to him, with plenty of rope, so that when the body has gone down, they know where to look for it when it shall have ascended again.
It was not long after the sinking of the body that a cry was heard from the Pequod's mast heads, announcing that the Jungfrau was again lowering her boats, though the only spout in sight was that of a finback, belonging to the species of uncapturable whales, because of its incredible power of swimming.
Nevertheless, the finback's spout is so similar to the sperm whales that by unskillful fishermen it is often mistaken for it.
and consequently Derek and all his host were now in valiant chase of this unnearable brute.
The virgin crowding all sail, made after her four young keels, and thus they all disappeared far to leeward, still in bold hopeful chase.
Oh!
Many are the Finbacks, and many are the Dereks, my friend.