Chapter 120 - The Deck Towards the End of the First Night Watch
AHAB standing by the helm.
Starbuck approaching him.
We must send down the main top sail yard, sir.
The band is working loose and the lee lift is half-stranded.
Shall I strike it, sir?
Strike nothing, lash it.
If I had sky sail poles, I'd sway them up now.
Sir, in God's name, sir!
Well, the anchors are working, sir.
Shall I get them inboard?
Strike nothing and stir nothing, but lash everything.
The wind rises, but it has not got up to my table lands yet.
Quick, and see to it.
By masts and keels, he takes me for the hunchback skipper of some coasting smack.
Send down my main-top sail-yard.
Ho, glue-pots!
Loftiest trucks were made for wildest winds, and this brain-truck of mine now sails amid the cloud-scud.
Shall I strike that?
Oh, none but cowards send down their brain-trucks in tempest-time.
What a hooroosh aloft there!
I would e'en take it for sublime, did I not know that the colic is a noisy malady.
Oh, take medicine, take medicine.