CHAPTER II THE CARPET-BAG I stuffed a shirt or two into my old carpet-bag, tucked it under my arm, and started for Cape Horn and the Pacific.
Quitting the good city of old Manhattan, I duly arrived in New Bedford.
It was a Saturday night in December.
Much as most young candidates for the pains and penalties of whaling stop at the same New Bedford, thence to embark on their voyage, it may as well be related that I, for
had no idea of so doing, for my mind was made up to sail in no other than a Nantucket craft, because there was a fine, boisterous something about everything connected with that famous old island, which amazingly pleased me.
Besides, though, New Bedford has of late been gradually monopolizing the business of whaling, and though in this matter poor old Nantucket is now much behind her, yet Nantucket was her great original attire of this Carthage, the place where the first dead American whale was stranded.
Where else but from Nantucket did those aboriginal whalemen, the Redmen, first sally out in canoes to give chase to the Leviathan?
And where but from Nantucket, too, did that first adventurous little sloop put forth?
Partly laden with imported cobblestones, so, goes the story to throw at the whales, in order to discover, when they were nigh enough, to risk a harpoon from the bowsprit.
Now having a night, a day, and still another night following before me in New Bedford, ere I could embark for my destined port, it became a matter of concernment where I was to eat and sleep.
Meanwhile it was a very dubious looking, nay, a very dark and dismal night, bitingly cold and cheerless.
I knew no one in the place.
With anxious gratinals I had sounded my pocket, and only brought up a few pieces of silver.
So, wherever you go, Ishmael," said I to myself, as I stood in the middle of a dreary street, shouldering my bag, and comparing the gloom towards the north with the darkness towards the south, wherever, in your wisdom, you may conclude to lodge for the night,
My dear Ishmael, be sure to inquire the price, and don't be too particular."
With halting steps I paced the streets and passed a sign of—The Crossed Harpoons.
but it looked too expensive and jolly there.
Further on, from the bright red windows of the Swordfish Inn, there came such fervent rays that it seemed to have melted the packed snow and ice from before the house, for everywhere else the congealed frost lay ten inches thick in a hard, asphaltic pavement.
Rather weary for me when I struck my foot against the flinty projections, because from hard, remorseless service the soles of my boots were in a most miserable plight.
Too expensive and jolly, again thought I, pausing one moment to watch the broad glare in the street and hear the sounds of the tinkling glasses within.
But go on, Ishmael," said I at last.
Don't you hear?
Get away from before the door.
Your patched boots are stopping the way.
So on I went.
I now by instinct followed the streets that took me waterward, for there, doubtless, were the cheapest, if not the cheeriest, inns.
Such dreary streets, blocks of blackness, not houses, on either hand, and here and there a candle, like a candle moving about in a tomb.
At this hour of the night, of the last day of the week, that quarter of the town proved all but deserted, but presently I came to a smoky light proceeding from a low, wide building
the door of which stood invitingly open.
It had a careless look, as if it were meant for the uses of the public.
So, entering, the first thing I did was to stumble over an ash-box in the porch.
Ha!
thought I, ha!
as the flying particles almost choked me.
Are these ashes from that destroyed city, Gamora?
But the crossed harpoons and the sword-fish?
This, then, must needs be the sign of the trap.
However, I picked myself up and, hearing a loud voice within, pushed on and opened a second interior door.
It seemed the great black Parliament sitting in Tophet.
All hundred black faces turned round in their rows to peer in beyond.
A black angel of doom was beating a book in a pulpit.
It was a negro church, and the preacher's text was about the blackness of darkness, and the weeping and wailing and teeth gnashing there.
Hush, male," muttered I, backing out, wretched entertainment at the sign of the trap.
Moving on, I at last came to a dim sort of light not far from the docks, and heard a forlorn creaking in the air, and looking up
saw a swinging sign over the door, with a white painting upon it, faintly representing a tall straight jet of misty spray, and these words underneath, the spouter in Peter Coffin.
Coffin?
Spouter?
Rather ominous in that particular connection, thought I.
But it is a common name in Nantucket, they say, and I suppose this Peter here is an emigrant from there, as the light looked so dim, and the place for the time looked quiet enough, and the dilapidated little wooden house itself looked as if it might have been carted here from the ruins of some burnt district.
and, as the swinging sign had a poverty-stricken sort of creak to it, I thought that here was the very spot for cheap lodgings and the best of pea-coffee.
It was a queer sort of place, a gable-ended old house, one side posited, as it were, and leaning over sadly.
It stood on a sharp, bleak corner, where that tempestuous wind, Eurycleidon, kept up a worse howling than ever it did about poor Paul's tossed craft.
Eurycleidon, nevertheless, is a mighty pleasant zephyr to anyone indoors, with his feet on the hob quietly toasting for bed.
In judging of that tempestuous wind called Uroclodon," says an old writer of, whose works I possess the only copy extented, maketh a marvellous difference, whether thou lookest out it from a glass window, where the frost is all on the outside, or whether thou observest it from that sashless window, where the frost is on both sides, and of which the white death is the only glazier.
True enough, thought I, as this passage occurred to my mind, old black letter.
Thou reasonest well.
Yes, these eyes are windows, and this body of mine is the house.
What a pity they didn't stop up the chinks and the crannies, though, and thrust in a little lint here and there.
But it's too late to make any improvements now.
The universe is finished, the copestone is on, and the chips were carted off a million years ago."
Poor Lazarus there, chattering his teeth against the kerbstone for his pillow, and shaking off his tatters with his shiverings.
he might plug up both ears with rags and put a corncob into his mouth, and yet that would not heap out the tempestuous Eurocleidon.
You're a climb, says old Dives in his red silken wrapper.
He had a redder one afterwards.
Pooh, pooh, what a fine frosty night!
How Orient glitters, what northern lights!
Let them talk of their Oriental summer climbs Of everlasting conservatories.
Give me the privilege Of making my own summer with my own coals.
But what thinks Lazarus?
Can he warm his blue hands By holding them up to the grand northern lights?
Would not Lazarus rather be in Sumatra than here?
Would he not far rather lay him down lengthwise along the line of the equator?
Yah, yah, gods!
Go down to the fiery pit itself, in order to keep out this frost.
Now, that Lazarus should lie stranded there on the kerbstone, before the door of dives, this is more wonderful than that an iceberg should be moored to one of the Moluccas.
Yet dives himself, he too lives like a czar In an ice palace made of frozen size, And, being a president of a temperate society, He only drinks the tepid tears of orphans.
But no more of this blubbering now, We are going a-whaling, And there is plenty of that yet to come.
Let us scrape the ice from our frosted feet, And see what sort of a place this spouter may be.