CHAPTER XXXIII.
THE SPITZENDEN.
Concerning the officers of the whale-craft, this seems as good a place as any to set down a little domestic peculiarity on shipboard arising from the existence of the Harpunia class of officers—a class unknown, of course, in any other marine than the whale-fleet.
The large importance attached to the Harpooneer's vocation is evinced by the fact that, originally in the old Dutch fishery, two centuries and more ago, the command of a whale-ship was not wholly lodged in the person now called the Captain, but was divided between him and an officer called the Specksender.
Literally, this word means fat-cutter usage, however in time made it equivalent to Chief Harpooneer.
In those days the Captain's authority was restricted to the navigation and general management of the vessel, while over the whale-hunting department, and all its concerns, the Spexunder, or Chief Harpooner, reigned supreme.
In the British Greenland fishery, under the corrupted title of Spexenier, this old Dutch official is still retained, but his former dignity is sadly abridged.
At present he ranks simply as Senior Harponeer, and the folks other, and, as such, is but one of the Captain's more inferior subalterns.
Nevertheless, as upon the good conduct of the Harponeers, the success of a whaling voyage largely depends.
and since in the American fishery he is not only an important officer in the boat, but under certain circumstances night-watchers on a whaling ground, the command of the ship's deck is also his, the da, therefore the grand political maxim of the sea demands, that he should nominally live apart from the men before the mast, and be in some way distinguished as a professional superior superior, though always by them familiarly
Now, the grand distinction drawn between officer and man at sea, is this the first life's aft, the last forward.
Hence, in whale-ships and merchantmen alike, the mates have their quarters with the captain.
And so, too, in most of the American whalers, the harpooneers are lodged in the after-part of the ship.
That is to say, they take their meals in the captain's cabin, and sleep in a place indirectly communicating with it.
Though the long period of a southern whaling voyage, by far the longest of all voyages now or ever made by a man, the peculiar perils of it, and the community of interests prevailing among the company, all of whom, high or low, depend for their profits, not upon fixed wages, but upon their common luck, together with their common vigilance, intrepidity, and hard work, though these things do in some cases tend to beget a less rigorous discipline than in merchantmen generally, yet never mind how much like in old Mesopotamian families
Indeed, many are the Nantucket ships in which you will see the skipper parading his quarter-deck with an elated grandeur not surpassed in any military navy, nay, extorting almost as much outward homage as if he wore the imperial purple and not the shabbiest of pilot-cloth.
And though of all men the moody captain of the Pequod was the least given to that sort of shallowest assumption, and though the only homage he ever exacted was implicit, instantaneous obedience, though he required no man to remove the shoes from his feet ere stepping upon the quarter-deck, and though there were times when, owing to peculiar circumstances connected with events hereafter to be detailed,
He addressed them in unusual terms, whether of condescension or enthrallum, or otherwise even Captain Ahab was by no means unobservant of confidence, nor, perhaps, will it fail to be eventually perceived, that behind those forms and usages, as it were, he sometimes masked himself, incidentally making use of them,
for other and more private ends than they were legitimately intended to subserve.
That certain sultanism of his brain, which had otherwise in a good degree remained unmanifested, through those forms that same sultanism became incarnate,
In an irresistible dictatorship, for be man's intellectual superiority what it will, it can never assume the practical, available supremacy over other men, without the aid of some sort of external arts and entrenchments.
always, in themselves, more or less paltry in base, this it is that forever keeps God's true princes of the empire from the world's hustings, and leaves the highest honors that this heir can give, to those men who become famous more through their infinite inferiority to the choice-hidden handful of the divine inert, than through their undoubted superiority over the dead level of the mass.
Such large virtue lurks in these small things when extreme political superstitions invest them, but in some royal instances, even to idiot imbecility, they have imparted potency.
But when, as in the case of Nicholas the Tsar, the ringed crown of geographical empire encircles, an imperial brain then, the plebeian herds crouch abased before the tremendous centralization.
Nor will the tragic dramatist who would depict mortal indomitableness in its fullest sweep and direct swing ever forget a hint, incidentally so important in his art as the one now alluded to.
But Ahab, my captain, still moves before me in all his Nantucket grimness and shagginess, and, in this episode touching emperors and kings, I must not conceal that I have only to do with a poor old whale-hunter like him.
And, therefore, all outward majestical trappings and housings are denied me.
O Ahab, what shall be granted thee?
It must needs be plucked at from the skies, and dived for in the deep, and featured in the unbodied air.