CHAPTER XXXVII.
SUNSET.
THE CABIN BY THE STERN WINDOWS Ahab, sitting alone and gazing out.
I leave a white and turbid wake, Pale waters, paler cheeks, where I sail.
The envious billows side-long swell To whelm my track, let them but.
First I pass.
Yonder by ever-brimming goblets rim The warm waves blush like wine, The gold brow plums the blue, The diver's sun-slow dived from noon goes, My soul mounts up, she wearies with her endless hill.
Is then the crown too heavy that I wear, This iron crown of Lombardy?
Yet is it bright with many a gem either wearer, See not its far flashings, but darkly feel, That I wear that, that dazzlingly confounds.
Tis iron that I know not gold, tis split too, That I feel the jagged edge galls me so, My brain seems to beat against the solid metal.
I, steel skull, mine the sword that needs no helmet In the most brain-battering fight.
Dry heat upon my brow, O!
Time was, when as the sunrise Nobly spurred me, so the sunset soothed.
No more, this lovely light, It lights not me, or loveliness is anguish To me, since I can ne'er enjoy, Gifted with a high perception, I lack the low, Enjoying power damned, most supply And most malignantly damned in the midst Of Paradise.
Good night, good night.
Waving his hand, he moves from the window.
"'Twas not so hard a task, I thought, to find one stubborn.
At the least, but my one-cogged circle fits into all their various wheels, and they revolve.
Or, if you will, like so many anthills of powder, they all stand before me, and I their match.
that to fire others the match itself must needs be wasting.
What I've dared, I've willed, and what I've willed, I'll do.
They think me mad, Starbuck does, but I'm demoniac.
I am madness maddened, that wild madness that's only came to comprehend itself.
The prophecy was that I should be dismembered and
I—I lost this leg.
I now prophesy that I will dismember my dismemberer.
Now, then, be the prophet and the fulfiller one.
That's more than ye, ye great gods, ever were.
I laugh, and who did ye?
Ye cricket-players, ye pugilists, ye death-berks and blinded bendigos.
I will not say as schoolboys do to bullies.
Take some one of your own size, don't pommel M. No, you've knocked me down, And I am up again, but ye have run and hidden.
Come forth from behind your cotton-bags, I have no long gun to reach ye.
Come, Ahab's compliments to ye, Come and see if you can swerve me.
Swerve me?
you cannot swerve me, I'll see swerve yourselves.
Man has you there.
Swerve me, the path to my fixed purpose Is laid with iron rails, whereon my soul is grooved to run.
Over unsounded gorges, through the rifled hearts Of mountains, under torrents' beds, unerringly I rush, Nought's an obstacle, nought's an angle to the iron way.