CHAPTER XIV NANTUCKET Nothing more happened on the passage worthy the mentioning so.
After a fine run we safely arrived in Nantucket.
Nantucket, take out your map and look at it.
See what a real corner of the world it occupies, how it stands there, a way offshore, more lonely than the Eddystone lighthouse.
Look at it, a mere hillock, an elbow of sand, all beach, without a background.
There is more sand there than you would use in twenty years as a substitute for blotting paper.
Some gamesome whites will tell you that they have to plant weeds there.
They don't grow naturally.
That they import Canada thistles.
They have to send beyond seas for a spile to stop a leak in an oil cask.
That pieces of wood in Nantucket are carried about like bits of the True Cross in Rome.
That people there plant toadstools before their houses to get under the shade in summertime.
That that wade of grass makes an oasis, three blades in a day's walk of prairie.
That they wear quicksand shoes, something like Laplander snowshoes.
That, that, tot, that.
But these extravaganzas only show that Nantucket is no Illinois.
Look now at the wondrous traditional story of how this island was settled by the Red Men.
Thus goes the legend.
In olden times an eagle swooped down upon the New England coast.
and carried off an infant Indian in his talons.
With loud lament the parents saw their child born out of sight over the wide waters.
They resolved to follow in the same direction, setting out in their canoes.
After a perilous passage they discovered the island, and there they found an empty ivory casket, the poor little Indian's skeleton.
What wonder, then, that these Nantucketers, born on a beach, should take to the sea for a livelihood.
They first caught crabs and quahogs in the sand-grown boulder.
They waded out with nets for mackerel more experienced.
They pushed off in boats and captured cod.
and at last, launching a navy of great ships on the sea, explore this watery world, put an incessant belt of circumnavigations round it, at Beepton, at Bering Strait, Straits Undone.
In all seasons, in all oceans, declare an everlasting war with the mightiest animated mass that has survived the flood, Mus Mostas, and Mus Mountainous.
that Himalayan salt-sea mastodon clothes with such portentousness of unconscious power, that his very panics are more to be dreaded than his most fearless and malicious assaults.
And thus have these naked Nantucketers, these sea-hermits,
issuing from their anthill in the sea, overrun and conquer the watery world like so many Alexanders, parceling out among them the Atlantic, Pacific, and Indian oceans, as the three pirate powers did Poland.
Let America add Mexico to Texas, and pile Cuba upon Canada, let the English overswarm all India,
And hang out their blazing banner from the sun.
Two-thirds of this tarracuous globe Are the Nantucketers, for the sea is his, he owns it, As emperors own empires, other seamen Having but a right of way through it.
Merchant ships are but extension bridges,
armed ones, but floating forts, even pirates and privateers.
Though following the sea as highwaymen the road, they but plunder other ships, other fragments of the land like themselves, without seeking to draw their living from the bottomless, deep itself.
In Antarctica, he alone resides, and riots on the sea he alone, in Bible language, goes down to it in ships.
To, and Fro, ploughing it as his own special plantation.
There is his home.
There lies his business, which a Noah's flood would not interrupt, though it overwhelmed all the millions in China.
He lives on the sea, as prairie cocks in the prairie.
He hides among the waves, he climbs them, as shammy hunters climb the Alps.
For years he knows not the land, so that when he comes to it at last, it smells like another world, more strangely than the moon would to an earthsman.
With a landless gall that at sunset folds her wings and is rocked to sleep between billows, so at nightfall the Nanta Keter, out of sight of land, furls his sails and lays him to his rest, while under his very pillow rush herds of walruses and whales.