CHAPTER FIFTY AHAB'S BOAT AND CREW THADDALA Who would have thought it, Flask?
cried Stubb.
If I had but one leg he would not catch me in a boat, unless maybe to stop the plug-hole with my timber toe.
Oh, he's a wonderful old man.
I don't think it's so strange, after all, on that account," said Flask.
If his leg were off at the hip now, it would be a different thing.
That would disable him.
But he has one knee, and good part of the other left, you know.
I don't know that, my little man.
I never yet saw him kneel.
Among whale-wise people it has often been argued whether, considering the paramount importance of his life to the success of the voyage, it is right for a whaling captain to jeopardize that life
in the active perils of the chase.
So Timerlane's soldiers often argued with tears in their eyes whether that invaluable life of his ought to be carried into the thickest of the fight.
But with Ahab the question assumed a modified aspect.
Considering that with two legs man is but a hobbling white in all times of danger, considering that the pursuit of whales is always under great and extraordinary difficulties,
that every individual moment, indeed, then comprises a perilings.
Under these circumstances is it wise for any maimed man to enter a whale-boat in the hunt, as a general thing the joint owners of the Pequod must have plainly thought not.
Ahab well knew that although his friends at home would think little of his entering a boat in certain comparatively harmless vicissitudes of the chase, for the sake of being near the scene of action and giving his orders in person, yet for Captain Ahab to have a boat actually apportioned to him as a regular headsman in the hunt above all
for Captain Ahab to be supplied with five extra men as that same boat's crew.
He well knew that such generous conceits never entered the heads of the owners, therefore he had not solicited a boat's crew from them, nor had he in any way hinted his desires on that head.
Nevertheless, he taken private measures of his own touching all that matter.
Until Cobacco's published discovery, the sailors had little foreseen it, though, to be sure when, after being a little while out of port, all hands had concluded the customary business of fitting the whale-boats for service.
When, sometime after this, Ahab was now and then found berserring himself in the matter of making full pins with his own hands for what was thought to be one of the spare boats, and even solicitously cutting the small wooden skewers, which, when the line is running out, are pinned over the groove in the bow, when the bow, when all this was over muddy.
But almost everybody supposed that this particular preparative heedfulness in Ahab must only be with a view to the ultimate chase of Moby Dick, for had already revealed his intention to hunt that mortal monster in person.
But such a supposition did by no means involve the remotest suspicion as to any boat's crew being assigned to that boat.
Now, with the subordinate phantoms, what wonder remained soon waned away, for in Wailer wonders soon wane.
Besides, now and then such unaccountable odds and ends of strange nations come up from the unknown nooks and ash-holes of the earth,
to man these floating outlaws of whalers of whalers.
And the ships themselves often pick up such queer castaway creatures found tossing about the open sea on planks, bits of wreck, oars, whale-boats, canoes, blown-off Japanese junks, and what not El Zebo might climb up the side and step down into the cabin to chat with the captain.
and it would not create any unsudoable excitement in the forecastle.
But be all this as it may, certain it is that while the subordinate phantoms soon found their place among the crew, though still, as it were, somehow distinct from them, yet that Herr Turban Fedala remained a muffled mystery to the last.
Whence he came in a mannerly world like this, by what sort of unaccountable tie, he soon evinced himself to be linked with Ahab's peculiar fortunes, nay, so far as to have some sort of a half-hinted influence, Heaven knows.
But it might have been even authority over him, over him, none knew.
But one cannot sustain an indifferent air concerning Fedala.
He was such a creature as civilized, domestic people in the temperate zone only see in their dreams, and that but dimly, but the like of whom now and then glide among the unchanging Asiatic communities, especially the oriental isles to the east of the continent, those insulated, immemorial, unalterable countries, which even in these modern days still preserve much of the ghostly aboriginalness of earth's primal generations, when the memory of the first man was a distinct recollection, and all men his descendants, unknowing whence he came, eyed