CHAPTER XXX.
MIDNIGHT FOR KISSLE.
HARPOONIERS AND SAILORS.
FORSAIL, RISES AND DISCOVERS.
THE WATCH STANDING, LOUNGING, LEANING AND LYING IN VARIOUS ATTITUDES, ALL SINGING IN CHORUS.
FAREWELL AND ADIEU TO YOU, SPANISH LADIES.
FAREWELL AND ADIEU TO YOU, LADIES OF SPAIN.
OUR CAPTAINS COMMANDED.
ONCE, DENOUNCE THE KIT SAILOR.
O boys, don't be sentimental, it's bad for the digestion.
Take a tonic, follow me.
And all follow.
Our captain stood upon the deck, A spy-glass in his hand, A viewing of those gallant whales That blew at every strand.
O your tubs in your boats, my boys, And by your braces stand, And we'll have one of those fine whales, Hand, boys, over.
Eight bells there, forward, To and dee, nay, and tuck it, sailor.
Avast the chorus, eight bells there, Be here, bell-boy,
Strike the bell eight thou pip, thou blackling, And let me call the watch.
I've the sort of mouth For that the hog's-head mouth."
So-so thrust his head down the scuttle.
Starbowley in said A-H-O-Y.
Eight bells there below tumble up.
Dutch sailor, grand snoozing to-night, Met thaw night for that.
I mark this in our old Mughal's wine, It's quite as deadening to some as filibing to others.
We sing thee sleep by.
Lie down there, like ground-tear butts, At M. again.
There take this copper pump, And hail M. through it.
Tell M. to avast Dreaming of their lassies.
Tell M. it's the resurrection.
They must kiss their last, And come to judgment.
That's the way that's, if thy throat ain't Spoiled with eating Amsterdam butter.
French sailor, Hist, boys, let's have a jig or two Before we ride to anchor in Blanket Bay.
What say ye?
There comes the other watch.
Stand by all legs.
Pip, little Pip, Hurrah with your tambourine.
Pip, salky and sleepy, Don't know where it is.
French sailor, Beat thy belly then and wag thy ears.
Jigot, men, I say Mary's the word, Gerard.
Damn me, won't you dance?
Form, now, Indian file, And gallop into the double shuffle.
Throw yourselves.
Legs, legs, Iceland's sailor.
I don't like your flour-meaty.
It's too springy to my taste.
I'm used to ice floors.
I'm sorry to throw cold water on the subject, but excuse me."
Maltese Sailor.
Me too.
Where's the girls?
Who but a fool would take his left hand by his right, and say to himself, How d'ye do?
Partners, I must have partners.
Sicilian Sailor.
I'd girls in the green.
Then I'll hop with you or turn grasshopper.
Long Island Sailor.
Well, well, you salkies, there's plenty more of us.
Hold corn when you may, say I. All eggs go to harvest soon.
The half of them dance to the tambourine, Some go below, some sleep or lie, Among the coils of rigging, Oaths aplenty, azure sailor.
Go it, Pip, bang it, bellboy, Rig it, dick it, stick it, quick it, bellboy, Make fireflies, break the jinglers, Pip.
Jinglers, you say?
There goes another, Dropped off, I pounded so.
China sailor, rattle thy teeth then, and pound away, of make a pagoda of thyself.
French sailor, merry mad, hold up thy hoopip till I jump through it.
Split jibs, tear yourselves.
Tesso, quake thee, smoking.
That's a white man.
He calls that Funko.
Humph!
I sieve my sweat.
Old men sailor, I wonder whether those jolly lads bethink them of what they are dancing over.
I'll dance over your grave, I will, that's the bitterest threat Of your night-women, that beat head-winds round corners.
O Christ, to think of the green navies, And the green-skulled crews!
Well, well, belight the whole world's a ball, As you scholars have it, and so tis right To make one ballroom of it.
Dance on, lads, your youngin' I was once, 3-D Nantucket sailor, spell O-hoo!
This is worse than pulling after whales in a calm gibbous.
Awith, Tash.
Cayce sees dancing and gathering clusters.
Meantime, the sky darkens, the wind rises.
Lasker Sailor By Brahma, boys, it'll be thou sail soon.
The sky-borne Haitha again just turned to wind.
Thou show'st thy black brow, Siva, Maltese Sailor, and shaking his cap.
But it's the waves the snow's caps turned a-jigget now.
They'll shake their tassels soon.
Now would all the waves were women.
Then I'd go drown, and chassis with them evermore.
There's not so sweet on earth heaven may not match it, As those swift glances of warm wild bosoms in the dance, When the over-arbouring arms hide such right bursting grapes.
Sicilian sailor, reclining, tell me not of it.
Hark ye, lad fleet, interlacings of the Limbs-lide, swayings, coings, flutterings, Lip, heart, hip, all grace, o'er unceasing touch and go.
La taste, observe ye, else come satiety.
Ay, pagan, Nuging, Tahitian sailor, reclining on a man, Hail, holy nakedness of our dancing girls, Ahiva-hiva!
All low-veiled, high-palmed Tahiti, I still rest me on thy mat, But the soft soil has slid, I saw thee woven in the wood my mat, Green the first day I brought ye thence, Now worn and wilted quite.
Ah me not thou, nor I can bear the change.
How then, if so, be transplanted to yon sky?
Here are the roaring streams from Pyrohede's peak of spears, When they leap down the crags and drown the villages.
The blast, the blast, upspine and meet it, Leaps to his feet, courted you sailor.
How the sea rolls, swashing gains the side, Stand by for reefing hearties.
The winds are just crossing swords, Pelmel they'll go lunging presently.
Danish sailor, Crack, crack, hold ship, so long as thou crackest, thou holdest.
Well done!
The mate there holds ye to it stiffly.
He's no more afraid than the Isleford at Cadiget, put there to fight the Baltic with storm-lashed guns, on which the sea-salt cakes.
Forth things.
Nantucket sailor, he has his orders, mind ye that?
I heard old Ahab tellin' he must always kill a squall.
Something is they burst a water spout with a pistol fire, you're shipped right into it.
English Sailor
Blood, but that old man's a grand old cove.
We are the lads to hunt him up his whale.
Ah, aye, aye, old mank, sailor.
How the three pines shake.
Pines are the hardest sort of tree to live when shifted to any other soil, and here there's none but the crew's cursed clay.
Steady, helmsman, steady.
This is the sort of weather when brave hearts snap ashore and keeled hulls split at sea.
Our captain has his birthmark.
Look yonder, boys.
There's another in the sky, lurid-like, you see, all else pitch-black.
Da goo, what of that?
Who's afraid of blacks afraid of me?
I'm queried out of it.
Spanish sailor, aside.
He wants to bully.
Ah, the old grudge makes me touchy, advancing.
I, Harponier, thy race is the undeniable dark side Of mankind devilish dark at that.
No offence.
Dagoo grimly, none.
St.
Jago's sailor.
That Spaniard's mad or drunk.
But that can't be, or else, in his one case, Our old mogul's fire-waters are somewhat long in working.
Fiveth none tucket, sailor.
What's that I saw lightning?
Yes, Spanish sailor, Nahu showing his teeth, Dagu's bringing, Swallow thy mannequin, white skin, white liver.
Spanish sailor meeting.
Him, knife thee heartily, Big frame, small spirit, all.
A row, a row, row, A row which lith a width, A row, a low, and a row, Aloft gods and men both brawlers.
Humph!
Belfast sailor, A row, a row, a row, The Virgin be blessed, a row.
Plunging with ye English sailor, Fair play!
Snatch the Spaniard's knife.
A ring, a ring, old mang-sailor.
Ready formed.
There, the ring to risen.
In that ring, cane-struck able.
Sweet work, right work.
No?
Why then?
God, mird'st thou the ring?
Meet's voice from the quarter-deck.
Hands by the halyards and top-gallon sails, Stand by to reef-top sails.
O, the squall, the squall, Jump, my jollies, they scatter.
Pip shrinking under the windlass, jollies,
Lord, help such jolly!
Krish!
Krash!
There goes the gypstay!
Blang!
Wanging!
God!
Duck low, Pip, here comes the Royal Yard.
It's worse than being in the World Woods the last day of the year.
Who'd go climbing after chestnuts now?
But there they go, all cursing.
And here I don't.
Find prospects to um— They're on the road to heaven.
Hold on hard, Jiminy, what a squall.
But those chaps there are worse, yet they are your white squalls, they.
White squalls, white whale, sure, sure.
Here have I heard all their chat just now, And the white whale sure, sure but spoken of once.
And only this evening it makes me jingle all over, Like my tambourine that anaconda of an old man Swore him in to hunt him.
O, thou big white god aloft there, Somewhere in yon darkness, Have mercy on this small black boy down here, Preserve him from all men that have no bowels to feel fear.